[Music]
all right hello and welcome everyone
welcome back to the second applied
active inference symposium it is the
second interval and it's july 31st 2022
in this second session
we are going to first feature a
presentation by bruno lara prediction
error dynamics a proof of concept
implementation
following that we'll hear from matt
brown
with a presentation real-time robotic
control through embodied homeostatic
feedback
the third presentation will be by adam
saffron on generalized simultaneous
localization and mapping gslam as a
unification framework for natural and
artificial intelligences and the final
presentation will be by jf klochter
towards a symbolic implementation of
active inference for lego robots we'll
then have some of those presenters
rejoin us in the final two or so hours
of this interval for a round table
discussion we'll also be joined by carl
first and there so thanks everyone for
watching live or in replay hope that you
add any comments
if you would like into the live chat
and
otherwise thanks to all of our
presenters and co-organizers for their
awesome work
and thanks so much for joining bruno
please take it away
yeah thanks a lot
for the invitation um
i was very surprised uh as as most of
our work so far
it's not directly related um
well it's not actually active inference
of course it's related
um
but um since we published a couple of
years ago
a paper well a paper that actually i'm
pre i'm presenting a bit of this results
here
um
well lots of lots of nice and
interesting people started to look into
this this implementation of of
prediction aerodynamics and it's
actually
the the part where
where um we could say it's a part that
we are taking out of all this framework
um to try to implement in our in our
robots in our agents
um
for for
i don't i i i don't know how much or how
many times you've heard this story of of
why we are doing this kind of
cognitive robotics or why we like to
call all this all this
research or this area cognitive robotics
and i like a lot this slide which kind
of summarizes what it's usually a long
introduction on the history of
artificial intelligence and robotics
um
and it just tells this this story of 50
years of research trying to figure out
how
can we have machines that are as
intelligent as humans
and it comes out that actually this this
upper part of the image
quite good resolve
rather
fast
we cannot say easily but but
it was more or less fast
and then we have the second part of the
slide like the bottom part which is what
comes out to be the most difficult
challenge for robotics no so what has to
do with interaction with the world you
have a small child that is capable of
handling this these objects in the
environment
and then you have this other robot that
can do it but at the time the moment
that you change the size the weight the
position whatever you want of the
of the pieces or of the chessboard
and you actually have a child that with
no problem can adapt himself to to the
challenge you know
and and and the the nerd joke is then on
the other side you have
another phd that
has to solve it if you do the same for
the robot you know
so in reality what was
supposed to or was thought to be
kind of the the heart the heart problem
which was having a robot reason and and
and solve problems
it came out to be quite the the
not so difficult to solve tasks and and
we can talk about
uh more difficult challenges
that have already been
passed
um
such as i don't know playing go which is
way harder than than chess
and we had alphago a couple of years ago
um well winning against
the human the human
champion
so
we like to think that we are we are
doing now uh things differently
we are having robots uh that interact
with the world that interact with what's
going on around
and and they learn through this
interaction
and of course that
gives us lots of challenges and lots of
things that we have to solve
um
so
now i come from from from this
yeah you could think now as an old
school of internal models
um uh
we we we work in in this um
in this field for for quite quite
already some years
and and it's this this this part of the
world where there is inverse and forward
models
um uh
for control of course and and they are
they are thought to be behind all these
all these important issues in in humans
and since since the beginning of my
career we've been doing implementations
of different types of of
um
of tools for for these robots but always
based
on these inverse and forward models so
just just a quick reminder for for those
that might not be
um
very very
much into this this type of models so we
had a sensory situation whichever it is
whatever it is and we have a desired
sensory situation we have an inverse
model
that takes as input does those two
things the the the sensory situation at
time t of course
the sensory situation at time t plus one
which is the desired
and the inverse model is going to tell
us uh what's the motor command that
needs to be performed to go from here to
here right and
then we have a forward model that takes
the sensory situation at time t and the
motor command at time t
and gives us
the prediction of what's going to happen
with this sensory situation
and so
we have a prediction error when we well
we have lots of errors but
um we we are interested on on
particularly this um error which is
the difference between what we actually
predicted and what happened in the world
so
we've been doing this for for quite a
while
uh um
well we've also used this this this
prediction back as a sensory situation
and we can get long-time predictions
what we called we can do lots of
comparisons between what we wanted and
what actually happened and
lots of different errors but as as you
know and well now everyone works with is
actually this error
like the difference between the world
and
what actually i predicted
um
yeah and so
that's that's that's what we
can say we have in common some years uh
after after
well some years ago actually we came
across all these all these ideas of
prediction uh
um
producer reproductive processing
and we started to to
to dig into it to see what actually we
could use for our models what what could
be useful for
for improving our models and our our uh
our agent's behaviors
and uh we have lots of doubts lots of
lots of questions
but
one of the first things that we've done
so far is to look into what happens with
the error as as
an agent is executing an action
sorry
um
but first i
i'd like you to walk you through
one of our our implementations well
first
where where is actually the um what you
could call the
the the crows uh areas
of what we believe it's it's important
in this case
when we have active inference and
prediction error minimization
so
most of us are very familiar with this
kind of um
representation of of what's happening
actually
during during action
uh and we actually believe that
prediction a minimizing prediction error
is what leads to belief updating so
like the change in a prior belief
encoded as a posterior belief and this
is actually informational gain so this
means learning right
so
in active inference the expected futures
their states are fulfilled through
action execution we know and this
associated expected prediction error is
minimized by actively sampling sensory
information and so the the important
part for us is this expected prediction
error
and we believe the attribute of a policy
which can be epistemic and instrumental
in in case this is this action is
novelty searching it's reflecting its
epistemic affordance and we could say
it's acting for information
uh in case of preference searching no
this reflects instrumental affordances
and its action for reward
so in words of of kirbenstein we can we
can think of active inference as the
process
of selecting relevant affordances
so those which are expected to minimize
prediction error in a context-sensitive
manner yeah
so
what we've done actually or what we
wanted to to
actually implement
uh is
how these how these um
expectations about the the
the dynamics of the error um
cause or are related to feelings to to
to these
um
embodied feelings and we believe they
they allow a sensitivity so how well or
how bad an agent is doing at improving
the grip on what is relevant in the
landscape of affordances
so the sensitivity to changes in the
rate of prediction error reduction is
what we call a prediction aerodynamics
and
we can say the steeper the slope the
faster the rate of reduction
um
and we see some some like uh
yeah
examples
just just very uh very simple so in in
red in in black we could see the actual
error as as like as the action is
executing
and then we have a slope associated to
this error so
what we don't want what the agent
doesn't want is this error increasing
having a positive slope
um
and
on the other hand the error is
decreasing then we have this slope and
this is actually what we
what we are looking for
so prediction errors are manifested as
changes on affect
so if the rate of prediction error is
faster than expected we have a positive
balance and we have an action policy
which is more precise
uh one in the case that the error is
slower than expected or is increasing
unexpectedly we have a negative violence
and an action policy which is less
precise
so
just just walking you through a couple
of implementations that we have done
the first one is just kind of
an example of of this mix that we are
trying to have
the error is used for learning but we
have a very simple um
implementation of
self-organizing maps
we call it the
self-organized internal models
architecture
the the nice thing on this architecture
is that it actually
sort of doesn't have to have an inverse
model what we have is a an um
self-organizing map that organizes the
motor
sensor information
and on the other hand we have a visual
sensory information which is also
organized
in the same another self-organizing map
and then we have what we call a
multi-modal representation and in this
multi-modal representation we have
associations we have associations
between
a sensory situation another sensory
situation
and a motor command
so you could think of this as
an inverse forward model pair but it's
actually not encoded as such so we just
have associations between sensory
situations and motor commands
and so we we thought this was very
interesting and we use it for example
for psychotic control
so the robot has some
initial sensory situation which is the
stimulus somewhere in the in in its in
its uh field of view
and what we need or what what the robot
wants is to phobiate the stimulus no so
this is the
sensory situation the desired one
and
we ask
this self-organizing maps architecture
what we need to do so to bring
the stimulus from here to here
and it's executed and it's not very
precise so it comes close to the center
of the image
and then we use this as the new sensory
situation
then we have the same target
we again ask the architecture what what
do we need to do and then it comes very
close so after 100 runs you can see that
the robot this is the
starting situation in red we have the
first
prediction and execution and in green we
have the second prediction and execution
so it's it's it's a very nice simple
architecture that actually works as i
said before it works like a forward
model but it can also work as an inverse
model
uh we use prediction error to learn
and so
we we could use it as some kind of
modular um
architecture
we can put more maps
and and
in this case we have the position of the
head visual stimulus the position of the
arm
and what the robot can actually do is
find the the the stimulus somewhere in
the space
and then bring it to the to the center
kind of obviate it and then actually
bring the arm also there so we have all
these associations between movements of
the head movements of the arm
movements of the eyes
and all these get associated and are
coded as initial and ending positions
um
[Music]
okay so
the next question or the next thing we
tried to do was how can we use
prediction aerodynamics
to guide learning and and this was this
paper we presented a couple of years ago
in in epirope
was actually guidos kilachi that
presented it
which is our co-author
so it's a work um
well by guido alejandra syria which is
also a colleague and myself
and what we did there is
um i i won't uh work on the on the
i won't tell you much about the
the
maps or the or the kind of networks that
were used and in detail the important
part is uh what we see here
so
we have
a very simple robot this is what you
could see here it's a 2 two degrees of
freedom um camera mounted on
on a
sort of artificial field
uh where we have lots of lots of plants
and
the the the robot moves towards a
specific destination so it looks it
wants to look at some at some image at
some point
um
and so we have for each movement for
each goal sorry for each goal
we have a prediction error
here
so we organize the goals in a sum of
course the goals sorry are encoded using
a an auto encoder we use the middle part
of the encoder to
have represented the goals here and the
important part is each each one of these
goals has some prediction error dynamics
yeah and so
we go back again to our inverse model
and forward model
and execute the command the motor
command and we get
our we do our prediction and we get an
error
between what we wanted and
what happened
the interesting part and what became
kind of nice and that was what we wanted
to implement what we were thinking about
is
we append this prediction error to as a
sort of a buffer
and
this buffer
once that it contains more than four
predictions we do a linear regression
and actually what we get is an indicator
of the progress uh
how good are we doing so it's kind of a
tendency for for for
for learning so
when we have a negative slope it
actually means we are going towards the
goal we are doing fine
so
progress is increasing and it means
there is a positive emotion
and we remain on this goal
so learning is going fine when the when
the slope is positive so the activities
away from the goal there is no progress
the error keeps increasing
so we have
what we could see as a negative emotion
and
something that can be encourages them to
switch to switch goal
um
so we have a positive slope means
increase the size of the prediction
error dynamics buffer this was one of
the
sorry that was uh something of
kind of interesting and
and very uh yeah new in in in in this in
this field in this area we haven't
thought about it before and what we
actually did is okay what happens if if
my if my
slope is positive it means i'm doing
very bad at this task and what i'm going
to do is i'm going to increase the size
of this buffer
yeah
when when we have a negative slope it
means okay i'm doing fine
so i'm going to decrease the size of
this buffer
so what we are actually doing is
adjusting dynamically the size of this
monitoring window and and and we're
doing that depending on how things are
going with respect to what we are
actually expecting
so if the prediction error increases we
have a positive slope and we do a more
frequent evaluation of the feedback
this allows a quick correction of the
action
and
it can lead to satisfaction in case
where we we managed to to
to do it better and induces abandoning
the goal so after in this case after a
number of iterations interactions
uh
where the error is not decreasing the
error keeps increasing
then we can change
we can switch goals and
we could say we are trying to avoid
frustration
so
through intrinsic motivation what we try
is search for a new goal
when the prediction error decreases we
have a negative slope
we don't need to
to be evaluating the feedback so so
frequently
and we can free resources for the agent
to do something else there is no more
prediction error so that means we've
achieved our goal so
learning happen learning occur
again
we search for a new goal now
so
when we select a new goal we give
priority to those that have a negative
slope which is kind of a steep in the
prediction aerodynamics and we have some
examples here of how
the error moves
uh
as we are moving in in in in the world
and how the buffer size increases when
the error increases and then it
decreases uh how when when the slope now
again changes
so that was that was one of the first
things we did and now actually adam
invited us to this to this uh special
issue that he did in frontiers
and um we we published there a paper
which is actually well at the beginning
it was about something else and then we
ended up with this with this
with this model presenting this model
uh this is this is just uh an idea that
we have
which actually encloses this part that i
talked about about the slopes
and the expected error
so what what we are what we are
suggesting here is that
um
[Music]
i don't know how much time we have if i
can go into detail on this but um let's
let's try something very fast so we have
an agent that has maybe
physiological needs in case the agent
doesn't have physiological needs
through intrinsic motivation
we want to do something new we want to
do
search around the world then we go to
what we call
the environmental context which brings
us to this field of affordances
uh where there is
loads of actions and each action each
each task has some
expected expected aerodynamics
we go to a task related context which
comes from selecting the task and then
we do some planning of sensory motor
sequences we start acting on the world
and we get some error
as we execute this task
then we have
two types of monitoring we have
the typical um
momentarily say error
that helps us
go through the planning and correct
the the execution of the task and we
have a a window
of prediction error dynamics which is
compared to the expected error that this
section had
and according to that
is that we are going to go to these
emotions
that tells us no the the error is
increasing we have this slope here so we
go back to another task
uh before like of course checking then
if something has changed we still have
physiological needs or we don't if the
error is not so greatly increasing it's
more or less going fine then we go back
to this same
uh planning to the same
action
so it's it's a very
uh very very nice uh
model that we thought of it's it's it's
it's on the it's on the make
uh
and we have many ideas uh
from bringing this
box diagram into into the world and and
in our in our
idealistic uh
uh
dream what we are thinking on is
something
actually based on soymag we haven't
implemented this yet but it's something
based on this oima but now we have lots
of other modules we have
uh some interceptive
internal model representation extra
receptive um
model representation
and this is actually wrong but anyway so
in this site we have all the receptive
information the interceptive information
and we have some policies and a task and
some error
this error is going to tell us how we
are doing
how we can stay on the task
uh if the error is too big then we can
change tasks so it's a bit of a mixture
between the the the previous thing i
told you and and this is how it could
look in
what happens on a top down so when we
have a task
this task is going to activate some
policies and these policies are going
down
um
[Music]
to act on the world we have again again
uh some error coming up and this error
is somewhat somehow coded here
there is some monitoring so that we can
go on in our policies this is the
momentanus error if the error is very
big then we can go back here
um
ah sorry so this is top down and and
this is actually bottom up no it's
actually the error coming up all the way
and coding here
and uh
yeah and this is how we start the cycle
with some task policies and everything
else that is happening in the world
so i think that
we can we can we can stop there
i hope it's it's clear we don't have
direct questions from the audience as
i'm not seeing anyone or
i'll ask you uh one question otherwise
no we have no direct questions but we
can um
definitely accumulate them for the round
table
yeah
what is the relationship between
prediction error minimization and free
energy
um
well i i think it's just like part of
the process uh uh i i don't know what
you mean i mean
within the whole thing of of
whatever you want free energy um
everything that is happening the
difference between the expected
uh states and what actually happened in
the world so
we always have in in inactive inference
or in free energy you always have an
error happening in in what's happening
what's in what's
yeah what is happening in the in the
action of the in the world
so
through
this prediction error
is how you are we we believe it's going
to happen like the learning is going to
occur
i don't know i don't know if
yes that's awesome well
yeah yeah thank you very much hope to
see you very soon
yeah we'll see you like in in two hours
or so
excellent see you soon
yeah okay thank you very much hope to
see you very soon
all right welcome everyone we are back
this next presentation is going to be by
matt brown real robotic control through
embodied homeostatic feedback so matt
thank you very much for co-organizing
and for also joining to present and
please take it away
uh yeah thank you uh for having me here
and that was a really great talk renault
um i have some follow-up questions for
later um but yeah thanks for coming and
uh my name is matt i'll be taking
talking a bit about um a long-running
research project and uh i hope you guys
find this interesting um
this here's a quick high-level
description of the project project um
it's kind of an alternate way of looking
at the generative modeling process built
around homeostasis from the bottom up uh
this approach is very different a bit of
an orthodox approach and i'll be going
into a bit of detail about how this
works um you could probably read it but
the short version is based on theories
of ross ashby and his homeostat and it's
a new kind of adaptive model that uses
uh learns via homeostatic feedback
through an environment and it's uh
and itself uh and i'll be showing some
demos about applying this to robotic
control uh that i've been working on
lately
uh just a quick agenda um i'll be
talking a bit about uh the project
background uh where it came from because
it is kind of unusual i figured some
background might be useful uh then i'll
be talking about um how homeostats uh
build network self models um and what
that means and how those function and
then i'll be talking about plugging
those into environments uh and how
embodiment works and how synchronization
functions uh in this process uh and then
i'll be doing some uh demonstrations uh
showing this working with robotics
um yeah so just to give you background
on myself uh i'm a computer scientist
mostly i'm not much of an academic i
have a few published papers but not on
this particular topic um
i've been obsessed with the mechanisms
of thought for most of my life um i
i've worked in the video game industry
for about a dozen years uh and then
worked in deep enforcement learning for
a number of years um and also uh about
20 years ago was uh worked in software
radio uh at the spectrumware project
which became genie radio that'll be
relevant later um today i'll be talking
about uh work that's uh now going on
going at my uh startup thoughtforge and
talking a bit about the history uh will
help explain what i'm doing i think uh
this started about uh 2006-2007 uh with
um deep learning was kind of new and was
kind of uh the new hot thing i did a big
deep dive into it really excited about
it uh but i was in fact quite uh
dissatisfied and i felt that um
deep learning and the this approach of
using neural networks didn't really
provide much insight to how learning
works in in natural systems uh and even
in the last few years i feel like we
have this amazing hammer with deep
learning and everything suddenly uh
looks like nails uh and i feel like we
need to take a step back and look
critically at what we're what problem
we're trying to solve so for me uh i was
looking for new approaches in the nature
of uh agency and goals uh goals in terms
of what what are they and how do they
manifest in nature um semantic
information versus raw information how
do bra sensory signals become meaningful
uh and also uh i wanted more insight
into how time played into this learning
process uh and i was in particular
looking for media agnostic approaches um
not neurons specifically how do plants
in single-celled organisms um deal with
their world uh so i started by reading a
lot um uh going back in time chaos
theory i was a big fan of i ran into
matarana and varela and autopisos and i
was really excited about that but it was
too abstract for me as an engineer i
think to tackle and so i kept going
until i got to
homeostasis and cybernetics and
particularly a cyberneticist named ross
ashby um and i basically became obsessed
with ross ashby and you know to still am
to a certain degree uh and he's not a
part of most computer science programs
so um he's quite well known outside of
computer science but i felt um is not
part of my own uh
education uh and he's most known for
things like the the law of requisite
variety and the good regulator theorem
uh and those will be common themes um
uh in the next 30 minutes or so um so
what i started doing is pouring through
ashby's technical journals recreating
his work in a particular device called
the homeostat um so this is just a quick
slide to tell people about uh the
homeostatin aspie uh no doubt many
people watching this probably are
familiar with ashby and perhaps the
homeostat uh but it's worth going over
briefly regardless um if you look up on
wikipedia it'll say homeostat is one of
the first devices capable of adapting
itself to the environment and it
exhibited behavior such as habituation
reinforcement and learning through its
ability to maintain homeostasis in a
changing environment um
ashby viewed uh you know learning as
adaptation and stability um and was
described as an isomorphism generating
machine and most importantly for me um
it uses feedback to generate hemostasis
via a property called ultra stability um
so i'll be talking about that here
there's a description here from one of
his books about it uh but um it is quite
tricky to re reproduce i had to go to
his uh personal technical journals um
and lots of iteration before i got it
working um the key for me uh was ultra
stability which is a very strange kind
of property but it is the individual
node property within this four node
homeostat that enabled this general
property this group property of
homeostasis to take place uh and it's
part of the function of how oops let me
go back
uh it's part of the uh function of how
the homeostat works uh and it's in the
property
implemented by individual nodes uh using
a simple set of rules that gives rise to
group homeostasis uh it's comprised of a
double feedback loop where like the low
level feedback loop performs like a
linear transformation and then a high
level feedback loop
modifies this linear transformation uh
and is designed to seek equilibrium
meaning output of zero which is you can
if you think of the um this each of
these nodes as seeking um uh uh uh
equilibrium of a state of zero um
every
choice of a linear transformation is a
prediction of a type and so uh the
result of this uh linear transformation
every at every moment uh accumulates
prediction error uh as uh as it seeks a
zero prediction error so um it's kind of
an interesting goal driven
process that uh works through multi uh
group process um
this is just a more in-depth description
of uh the homeostat basically
constructed of four individual
ultra-stable nodes um
and the network as a whole creates an
adaptive dynamical tractor set as a
self-consistent reinforcing self-model
um
ultimate stability powers its race of
states disabled states space space
exploration uh through like the law of
representative variety uh and can be
seen as a network of uh reciprocal
reciprocal constraints
um
this is just an interesting letter uh
from uh
uh alan turing to ashby uh back when
they were members of the ratio club um
and ashley was getting some notoriety um
hearing um basically disagreed with
ashley's approach and you know this
letter here he suggests that ashby
simply uh so uh simulate his homeostat
in his uh tiering machine um and while
true uh i think this uh actually was a
bit taken aback by this um
because it kind of misses the point um
at the time the debate was all about
analog versus digital computation um and
you know uh what was useful to the war
effort uh was most critical um but there
was a bit of a conflation here i think
in terms of what aspect was trying to
create which was something more along
the lines of universal adaptation or
universal cognition maybe um versus
turing's universal computation uh and
you know uh i feel like this conflation
of issues still haunts us today with
deep learning and whether or not they're
intelligent um
so how do you build them so uh
essentially i took tyrion's advice and
simulated um
and particularly uh 20 years ago as part
of the spectrum wear project which uh
you know kind of pioneered software
radio uh which is now part called geniu
radio uh and so i kind of stole
methodologies from this approach where i
you know i created the homeostat as a
digital simulation of a continuous
analog system or device um
and so that's kind of the approach i
took
um i started by pointing through ask
these technical journals um you know and
experimented with different
implementations and approaches of his
direct analog machine um once this was
functional uh it was simple enough to
abstract down to very simple kind of
minimal process um once it's functional
you can start taking pieces out and see
what what breaks it and what doesn't uh
and eventually this uh effectively
simplified down to a dynamical attractor
definition for ultra stability uh that
could be connected into arbitrary
network topologies uh and the network as
a whole can be kind of seen as a self
model uh each node is trying to protect
its neighbor as it seeks equilibrium um
and the local ultra stability tunes
nodes local connections and the
resulting positive and negative
feedbacks loops that it is personally a
part of and ultra speedy tunes these as
a group of these overlapping feedback
loops such that they reach the
homeostatic equilibrium uh and that
means that the uh local prediction
accumulated prediction error drops to
zero as well the as well as the output
uh uh from each node uh and these
overlapping loops become
self-reinforcing and self-repairing uh
and it's uh this final self-predicting
set of loops that you know uh maintains
a self-model uh at homeostatic
equilibrium this model converges and
considered self-consistent um it is
composed of um
these homeostatic feedback loops that
maintain the network at a critical state
uh meaning that um the network is highly
sensitive to prediction error i mean the
smalling the smallest prediction error
can trigger global structural changes
amongst these feedback loops and this
process can also be seen as
synchronization
which i can talk about uh a bit later
um so let me show a quick demo i'm gonna
skip the original homeostat here and i'm
going to um
uh show a quick demonstration of what
this actually looks like for a 20 node
homeostat it takes a bit longer and it's
a little more
demonstrative so let me let me switch
briefly here and apologize for the delay
while i get this up
um
cool all right so let me just describe
what you're seeing here uh you're seeing
20 single dimensional graphs you could
uh this is the accumulated local
prediction error at each node of the 20
node homeostat
you can also think of this as one
20-dimensional uh dynamical attractor or
20 single-dimensional uh dynamical
tractors these are also kind of you
consider these as phase space graphs um
for each of the nodes uh so what you're
seeing here is i have a pause i'm going
to move it along slowly this is slowed
down uh on purpose uh and what you'll
see is they start off very chaotically
um and you know what'll happen is a
couple nodes will start stabilizing uh
then more will start stabilizing and
then eventually uh the entire network
will converge to
zero prediction error now this is
unconnected to an environment so it's
just
predicting itself uh one thing i like to
do here and i don't know how many people
else are going to find this interesting
i want to show a little in-depth look at
what this final convergence and collapse
to zero looks like um so um what i'm
going to do is i'm going to
change this to auto scaling the the
graphs meaning that as it goes to zero
you'll see the the
the graph ranges drop uh and uh and what
you'll should see is this uh usually
there's a pattern forms amongst the
output nodes um that is kind of
consistent with every drop what you'll
see is that you know um it's kind of
hard to see with 20 nodes especially
i've gone a little too far we're already
at e negative 20 here um but what you're
seeing is you're seeing the 20
dimensional drop to zero and there's
kind of like a cyclical pattern to this
uh and every time it goes through this
pattern it drops down another order of
magnitude and this will go all the way
down to uh the floating point error of
my computer which is about negative 46 i
believe uh and then it basically fails
to function at that point because it
can't tell the difference uh floating
point error uh it can no longer function
so
and the whole thing kind of falls apart
there um but um that kind of shows you a
bit about the process um let me go
quickly back to the
uh the slides
so yeah that just kind of showed you a
slowed down version of the 20
dimensional homeostat and i want to show
the 20 dimensional because it happens a
lot slower and it's a little uh easier
to see what's going on with four nodes
it's almost instantaneous and it's hard
to see the progression
um okay
um so that seems like a lot of work for
a model that doesn't really do anything
is a connective environment so you know
we have this model that can adapt this
internal structure to reach homeostatic
equilibrium through kind of a
self-synchronization process um how do
we use this to drive behavior and you
know this next step took me a few years
uh even though it's kind of conceptually
simple um but don't worry it'll uh it'll
get complex really quickly
the short version is sensors and motors
kind of define how the agent is embedded
into an environment
and
the network topology defines the
adaptive capacity of the homeostatic
agent's model uh sensitive definitions
provide a mechanism to influence the
behavior of the system by providing uh
priors in the form of preferred
environmental states these act is kind
of like tela dynamic priors uh
externally defined dynamic set points
for the homeostatic adaptation um the
motor definitions provide clinical
affordances for modifying the
environment that provides the basis for
future sensory predictions
uh the preferred states of the sensors
become the preferred outcomes of the
motors and the model's behavior is
biased as as desired
this is probably most people on this
active inference symposium are probably
familiar with this idea
uh this slide is put together um
for the benefit of people who are kind
of familiar with traditional deep
learning and neural network approaches
to contrast how these networks function
differently
because it's a bit hard for people to
get their head around um the first
it is probably the most obvious is
there's no back propagation here uh only
ultra stability which is kind of a local
rule um this uh leads to huge sample
efficiency and uh the learning is very
structured meaning you don't have to you
know diffuse learning across you know
thousands or millions of parameters you
know you only have to model the part of
the uh you don't have to update the part
of the model that
is mispredicting or you know is part of
a misprediction um
the other thing to notice is that um
this is not a temporal most uh neural
networks and you know like deep learning
networks are kind of disembodied
atemporal processes um this is very much
a temporal process uh you know
signals take time to move from one node
to another which makes it inherently the
whole thing very temporal uh the
resulting temporal relationships are
important actually um spatial
relationships of sensors and motors end
up getting encoded into temporal
relative temporal relationships within
the sensory signals um such and also
vice versa signal timings of the
propagating signals within the network
can translate into different physical
spatial relationships amongst the output
motors uh for example or the input
sensors um so there's a relationship um
between uh temporal location relative
timing of signals and the spatial
location of sensors and motors and the
physical embodied
agent
um different in the you know just to
kind of you know push on that a little
farther the different regions within
this larger homeostatic network will
then be sensitive to different sets of
motors and sense of sensors um based on
their physical uh relative location um
and uh by contrast you know
you know deep learning deep enforcement
learning uh deep reinforcement learning
for example is an attempt at adding
temporality to an otherwise a temporal
static uh deep learning models um you
know the other way to compare these two
is you know deep learning models are
generally trying to be general function
universal function approximators uh in
uh where this is much more uh
generative and inherently temporal uh
the very learning is very very different
um and uh just to expand a bit more on
the topics from the previous slide um
the network diagram here on the right is
very oversimplified uh network and it's
just a meant to visually explain how to
think about some of these networks uh
there's no forward or backward no front
back top bottom um only kind of relative
relative location from other nodes and
from sensors and motors perhaps more
relevantly um and
it is um you know common for people to
look at the learning process as a
sequential flow of processing like
sensing perceiving then acting uh or
plan planning than acting uh and instead
you know you have to kind of think of
this as all happening at the same time
merging together is kind of one whole
perceptual motor system uh not a
traditional uh sandwich uh model time
simply advances and we simulate the
analog systems as signals propagate
across the network uh and so you know
you don't get input from the sensors
calculate the network and get alpha
motors you get you send them input to
the sensors you get out from the motors
base and those motor actions are
basically based on the generative
model's prediction of what it should be
doing already before having it even
sensed the world um
so
the you know what's interesting here
from the model point of view in terms of
how this homeostasis works is the
network's homeostatic feedback loops
come to be dependent on the expected
sensory signals uh meaning that the the
the sensory signals become entrained in
the homeostatic self-maintenance
processes um which kind of naturally
makes it grounded in the body experience
this uh and this you know homeostatic
self-maintenance process is composed of
the environmental signals themselves as
part of its predictions and expectations
um expectations and predictions for the
consequences of motor actions are
embedded in the signal sentence through
the sensors from deeper in the network
like on the right here and uh they're
sent to the sensors where expectation
meets reality and prediction errors
cascade backwards uh and modify the
internal structure of the model uh as
polynomials model update um these and
then motor actions are accompanied by
these parallel sensory prediction
signals that flow uh from the deeper in
the network uh the actions taken at any
moment are not based on the latest input
but based on predictions driven from
deeper in the network uh
from the same
places that the sensory expectations are
sent from uh this may be familiar to
those uh who who are you know think like
uh familiar with predictive processing
or perceptual control theory and the
idea here is that you know where the
sensors and motors meet the network you
know the the network itself is trying to
make those local prediction errors zero
meaning it's trying to anticipate the
actual sensory experience um through
kind of inverse modeling
um so another just kind of quick look at
uh you know how to look at this
homeostatic process is through
synchronization
this process can be seen as generating
an adaptive synchronization manifold
between an agent and an environment um
around minimization of prediction error
um this is kind of looking at
synchronization as prediction you know
when when a system when two sentences
are synchronized they can be thought of
as predicting each other anticipating
the other uh the others motions uh and
individual nodes using ultra stability
are using alter stability to learn how
to predict their neighbors and when that
equilibrium these nodes are kind of
synchronized through these feedback
loops um and the synchronization spreads
um from individual nodes to whole
network synchronization and ultimately
uh out from the motors and backing
through the sensors um in a
synchronization manifold between the
agent and environment um you know to say
it another way the overlapping feedback
loops interact and synchronize with each
other as part of this homeostatic self
maintenance and as these feedback loops
extend from motors to the environment
the sensors the model gains ability to
anticipate the consequences of its own
actions uh and the capacity to
synchronize internal states with
something in the external world the
synchronization means that you know
internal states will come to resemble uh
the in
one will come to resemble the internal
states of the other um this is kind of
along the lines of you know the good
regulator theorem um when at this you
know synchronized homeostatic state it's
also in this critical state i mentioned
this earlier um where it's stable uh but
it's sensitive to local prediction error
so the meaning that the the model uh
this critical state is maintained as
long as as long as local prediction area
is maintained within a certain threshold
um and but otherwise you know the
smallest prediction error can trigger
global kind of structural changes within
these feedback loops uh in order to
better predict the future uh you know in
order to maintain a synchronization
network must be able to converge to
equilibrium faster than the environment
can destabilize it um and so there's um
you know so there's update you know
network update rates where we have to
maintain um you know this kind of
fast movement and this kind of is in
line with the law of requisite variety
where we have to make sure that we can
explore state spaces faster than the
environment we're attempting to control
um
and as long as the homeostatic network
can re-establi establish these stable
feedback loops faster than
then this synchronization manifold will
be maintained uh and synchronization is
kind of an interesting thing um
especially in the context of um robotic
control um because you know once kind of
two elements are synchronized you know
let's say you have a sub network that's
synchronous synchronized then you know
two indirectly two nodes that are not
directly connected uh can end up
coordinating without any kind of
communication between the two because
they've been previously synchronized uh
their behavior will end up being
correlated as well um
and in case it's uh interesting to think
about um you know what is the structure
of these kind of feedback loops and this
you know generative model and the way i
like to think about it is
a dynamic holarchy meaning um you know a
hierarchy is kind of like uh you know a
top-down construction um but you know a
dynamic holocaust is more like a um a
bottom-up construction where the parents
are composed of the children and dynamic
in that as the children change their own
self-definitions the parents are
likewise changed so it's kind of
constantly shifting and changing over
time as the children redefine themselves
uh and this structure is very useful uh
as a gender model as allows a small
number of individuals to you know kind
of reshape the hierarchy very quickly as
it's part of an ongoing dynamic process
um cool so i'll switch over and do some
quick kind of uh demonstrations showing
how this ends up you know why would you
actually want to do this um you know
yeah why would you actually want to do
this especially in the context of
robotics um
so the first thing i'm going to show
is um let me just share here quickly
this is the demo i put together um a
couple years ago actually let me
let me shrink the screen a little bit so
it's not quite so much to share
uh this was put together a couple years
ago to kind of demonstrate you know why
would you do why would you do robotics
like this you know what is the point um
and you know what does robustness mean
and what does additivity mean uh in the
context of uh robotics so hopefully you
can see now on my screen this is just a
simple um
modification of an open ai gym called uh
reacher uh and what it's been modified
to add a single texture joint here uh
and
the reasons will be obvious here in a
minute um but um this is just a simple
task let's try the you know the model
has to get its end effector to the
target position and this is using these
homeostatic models here um but here's
what's interesting i can do and it
hasn't this model hasn't seen this
situation yet i can disable the outer
motor for example
and it will basically on the fly figure
out how to achieve the goal um you know
just by updating its internal model and
saying oh this motor doesn't work
anymore let me let me modify my my model
of the world i can turn that back on and
um he'll start using it immediately or
it will start using immediately i can do
the same with the internal motor
it can turn that off and so oops i did
not turn it off
there we go now now it's off
um yeah so and it just kind of figures
out oh okay the the inner motor i have
no longer have access to let me update
my model and i can again turn that back
on and it'll start using it again um so
this was just kind of a simple
demonstration i made a couple years ago
to show why you would want to do
robotics this way in that you can kind
of get this real-time adaptation to
unexpected situations um due to the the
generative model that's constructed this
way um now let me just scoot forward a
little bit to more recent work
um
and hopefully um the frame rate won't be
too bad over zoom
let me just
shrink the window a little bit in hopes
that helps
okay let me um
share this
the frame rate just feels a little rough
over over a zoom here um but this is all
just running locally on machine so this
is something a little more uh recent a
little more complicated we made the goal
a little bit more complica complex uh
and we've used a full six degree of
freedom arm here from like an uh this is
actually a fetch robot mobile arm um but
something a little more realistic than
like a toy problem uh and i'm just you
know continue periodically here
re-targeting the the desired angle for
this valve and so this is just a robot
that turns valves uh and what i've done
is that um i i can periodically change
the set point for its des you know where
how it sees the world basically use
defined goals by you know defining
preferred states of the world uh and
then the homeostatic model basically
figures out how to control the robot to
to uh to affect the you know the state
of the world that it wants um
i'm hoping here every 30 seconds it will
randomize the um the valve shape the
square one here is the simplest one but
let me add some
random motion and random orientation the
model has not seen this before either so
it just kind of learns on the fly how to
deal with this kind of moving shape as i
do it i can also do it with a sinusoidal
motion here so imagine it's on a
floating platform um where the rotation
and the uh position are kind of moving
through space um here we go now we got
something more interesting so now we
have it still moving through space it's
a circular valve here something a little
harder to turn um and what i'm going to
do is i'm going to make it very slippery
so imagine i've just poured oil over it
so if now it's having to deal with a
really really slippery valve here that
it has to turn and still manages to do
it even though it's really hard um but
you can get the idea here is you know uh
if you do the generative model in this
kind of sample efficient way you can
kind of um get natural um you know
adaptation to whatever it's kind of
experiencing in the moment here um
so
i think i've kind of i think this is
maybe maybe i'll do the random motion
again maybe that's interesting um
but yeah there's all sorts of stuff you
can kind of throw at this and go kind of
deal with it i apologize for the frame
right i'm going to blame zoom for that
um
so
cool all right good um
i don't think i have too much left
but
you know
next steps are uh basically improving
automation and tools um i'm working uh
my startup is basically developing this
for um for real world use uh in adaptive
situations where you need um fine motor
control uh and kind of uh dexterous
object manipulation in uncertain
environments um you know it's on the
technical side we're looking at you know
scaling up both specifications and
topologies which are related as well as
you know deeper temporal horizons in
both directions planning uh and ahead
and recall um but yeah that's um about
all i had for today uh and i look
forward to the questions during the uh
the um
round table in a little bit if anybody
has questions now i can talk to it as
well
i'm a little i went a little fast i
apologize
i'm a fast talker
it was great just maybe one preliminary
question
what settings do you see
these
uh kinds of implementations occurring in
first and then the other question
in order or if it's your preference is
how do you see the homeostatic network
related to the analytical
first principles foundations of active
inference as we know it today
yeah no um those are really good
questions and i you know i i didn't talk
much about active members because i
figured everybody else had kind of done
it pretty fairly um the use cases first
your first question um use kids we're
looking at are things that are just
beyond um the ability of uh current
robotics um the idea here is this
software could be put on you know any
old robot and kind of provide you know
um adaptive capabilities for certain
things um
you know we're pretty open-ended in
terms of what we're looking at in terms
of use cases uh right now our current
uses are in like um uh
uh energy uh and manufacturing uh
particularly um this is a fair amount of
stuff that still has to be done by
humans that could be pretty easily uh
moved into robots um
if they had you know a little bit more
capability uh and then in terms of how
does uh the homeostatic networks kind of
fit into the active inference uh
framework in general and i kind of
touched on it a little bit in terms of
how this uh these ultra stable nodes
work in the framework of homeostasis uh
if you kind of think of homeostasis as
the network trying to seek you know
global equilibrium um what this means
from the ultrastable nodes point of view
it means that it's um it's uh its local
output state is is zero and that local
output state is um the result of an
accumulation process of this linear
transformation so the idea here is this
ultra stable node what it's doing is
it's doing a search it's doing a search
through linear what are the right linear
transformations that make my local uh
state go to zero uh and so in that
context you can kind of think of every
time the um the ultra stable node
updates its local linear transformations
um this is updating its local model of
the world and making a new guess about
how the real world works uh and whether
or not that's useful for the purpose of
global prediction you know it depends on
whether or not it makes that local uh
value go to zero so there's there's a
lot of threads here in terms of um
expectations and um and
you know prediction error flowing
through the network um but it's a much
more distributed process like it's and
it's much less clear like um what each
node is is what part of the model each
node has taken place because you know
each node in the network uh when it's
changing its linear transformation what
it's actually doing is slightly
redefining all the feedback loops in all
the of all the sub networks in the
network it's in all the loops that flow
through that node it's making a small
change to so
um each node in a certain way then has
effect on all the other networks uh that
are connected through its feedback loops
and all those other nodes also have
impact on its uh signals that are
flowing through it uh and this is this
reciprocal process that kind of builds
this generative model i'm not sure if
that's particularly helpful
yeah that's great um if i could make one
more comment question then we'll bring
adam saffron on in just a minute or two
the letter that you showed was quite
interesting
and
i got the sense of this like
multi-generational titanic clash between
what you described as infinite
computation
in the discrete setting with the turing
tape and then infinite adaptation in the
continuous setting with the generalized
cybernetics and so i think that's a very
fascinating framing because what do
people say about computers and
continuous time systems we're going to
have to discretize
and so the implementation is stepwise
and that's what allows us to like
actually implement it on hard drives and
cpus and so on with the von neumann
architecture but then also in the
background or like even the water that
we swim in is this continuous time the
real time unfolding of perception
cognition action outside the sandwich
model outside of the discrete time
yeah i i i'm really glad to pick up on
that i wish i was more qualified to
speak on such topics i'm a computer
scientist so i i don't want to speak too
far outside my field um but yeah i think
you hit the nail on the head of my gut
instinct on it you know
um all right we'll take just a short
break and then come right back with adam
saffron
all right welcome back everyone
we are continuing on
with adam saffron generalized
simultaneous localization and mapping
gslam as a unification framework for
natural and artificial intelligences so
adam thanks a lot for joining and please
take it away
um thank you daniel so hello everyone
i'm adam saffron i am a research fellow
at
the johns hopkins university school of
medicine at their
center for psychedelic consciousness
research
and today i will be discussing
a grand unified theory
another one
but before i do um as was previously
mentioned and as is probably of interest
to
people watching this i recently
co-organized a special issue of
frontiers in neuro robotics with
inescipito and andy clark
most of the submissions are already in
for you to read and
that will be closing up soon
there's also another special issue
that i am co-organizing with other
active inferencers and fristonians
for royal society interface focus
on the subject of symmetries in mind and
life broadly construed
ranging from
symmetry breaking and dynamical systems
to
a gauge theoretic formulation of the
free energy principle
this is actively soliciting
contributions and so please contact me
if you have anything along those lines
so
uh in this work and throughout all of it
uh
my journey i've been trying to
understand the basis of autonomy and
biological and artificial systems um
do we have free will how does that work
could we build autonomous agents that
work like we do and have our capacities
these are the kinds of questions that
have motivated me
towards this end i have been
working on some
fairly ambitious projects such as
a theory of consciousness that tries to
bring together various theories
within the free energy principle and
active inference framework
and also
models of free will
in terms of the micro mechanics of
agency
across all of this work i take what i've
called a
marian neurophenomenological approach or
a neil seth calls it computational
neurophenomenology which
i think is a better name uh and roughly
the idea is you take the core aspects of
experience um seriously
as fundamental things to explain
and then you cross-reference this with a
multi-level uh
functionalist handling or a marion
handling
where you can simultaneously analyze the
system on
computational or functional levels with
the system um what the different aspects
are for their their adaptive
significance what their
the function they're serving this
algorithmic level the abstract way
the specific programs and operations by
which this is achieved
and the implementational level or the
physical realization of these and so the
idea is you take this multi-stack under
um understanding of cognitive systems
and you cross reference this with um
phenomenology taking experience
seriously and this is my general
approach and uh active inference um with
its associated process theories
basically checks boxes across all those
levels
you have the free energy principle you
have active inference and you have
predictive coding
and these various
claims of different degrees of
specificity really help to flush out
this mutually constraining multi-level
account of cognition
but
more recently i have been collaborating
with roboticists
and here are two particularly excellent
bio-bots tim verbalin and ozin kathal
and um a lot of these journeys uh we
encountered each other and um
there's increasing interest in
uh machine learning and artificial
intelligence and things like artificial
consciousness
you'll have people like bengio talking
about system two cognition and more um
recently even lacuna's been starting to
take these things on
uh with um his jepa architecture talking
about world models
of different kinds and how they might
serve the functions of artificial
consciousness
um but for my collaboration with tim and
ozin we've mostly been focused
on the specific problem of navigation
um specifically a problem known as
simultaneous localization and mapping
uh roughly the idea here is that um
where am i in space
and what kind of space is this
this is a fundamental question for any
active inference system any cybernetic
system
um but there's a kind of a problem here
and that
you're trying to map out the space
and situate yourself in it in the same
time simultaneously so but to map out
the space it helps to know where you are
in the space but to know where you are
in the space it helps to help to have a
good map of that space
and so there's various proposals for
different ways of bootstrapping yourself
to degrees of certainty of
what kind of maps or models are adequate
for situating you
in the world
in a particular location and this is
going to be important whether you're a
robot
navigating through the world or an
animal foraging for value
you got to know where you are
to know what to do
so
more recently
in this collaboration
which i've really found to be amazing
because uh i just i'm in awe of robotics
and what they can do it's kind of like
that feynman quote of what i cannot
build i would i
cannot build i do not understand well
they live that that's just what they do
all day long they're like introspecting
how do i work they're going into theory
and then they're actually building a
system in this back and forth iterative
process and so
the collaboration here was i'm looking
at what ways can um biological systems
and specifically focusing on the
hippocampal system what ways can these
inform navigation problems
um in this more recent paper that i'm
going to be focusing on more today
called
generalized simultaneous localization
mapping or gslam
we're reversing the flow a bit and the
idea is
more than
cognitive neuroscience and forming
robotics
it's looking more to robotics to inform
cognitive neuroscience basically
leveraging the the precision they have
with characterizing these problems and
the way they're in touch with the ground
truth of
engineering and physical moving systems
in the world
um using this to inform cognitive
neuroscience
and specifically the claim is that this
slam problem is fundamental and that it
may have structured a uh surprisingly
maybe shockingly broad range of
cognitive processes and that this might
be a fundamental a source of fundamental
principles for
understanding how high-level cognition
was achieved with high-level put in some
scare quotes but the idea is the things
that
humans seem to be or animals seem to be
particularly capable of doing relative
artificial systems and humans in some
ways even more so
and the properties we want to
recapitulate in artificial intelligence
and machine learning
uh so some precedent for this um came
from work with ratslam
a seminal work by um milford wyatt and
praiser so
i'm in this they uh look to the
the rat in this hippocampus and look at
look at its wayfinding and navigation
abilities and try to um basically
reverse engineer these uh there's a
really um excellent youtube video that
i'll post um i've watched it countless
times which just summarizes this process
of building up rat slam from like these
initial foundations of the ambition
and folding in more and more details
finding you know this isn't quite
working going back to the biology going
back to engineering and then actually
showing systems that um
do the same things as biological systems
inspired by those systems it's extremely
compelling um it kind of like you know
every time i watch that video i feel
like i get something new i wonder is are
these the steps that nature took and
evolving these systems i also kind of
felt like what have i been doing with my
life all this time like why didn't i
find roboticists sooner and started
talking to them
um so i'm very grateful to be part of
this symposium
uh
leighton and very grateful for uh tim
and ozin
and so
with their work with leighton slam uh
what they're doing is they're
tackling the slam problem using active
inference i'm not going to go into all
the details here but some of this was
discussed um there's parallels with some
of the architectures they were discussed
previously and tim touched on this
so you basically have an agent moving
through the world that has a variety of
views of what it's expecting to see and
poses
and this experience map is a trajectory
of the agent
through
space and time and then here would be a
generative model description in the
middle of this where you have these
conjunctions of posing of poses and
views which are unfolding um in this
series of transitions um adaptively
sculpted sculpted via your policies
but where there's this upper level which
is basically organizing this as spatial
temporal trajectories situating you in
some kind of map or graph of space
and uh
this
conjunction of pose and view um one of
the places i found to be compelling is
that um i've arrived at these as
basically the primary modalities i focus
on just from like looking at the systems
neuroscience but this um happens to be
the primary things that are focused on
for helping a robot to move through the
world and a
pose and view um and basically for
neuroscience i focus a lot on systems
such as the pecunius as potentially um
enabling something like a mind's eye and
the lateral prior courtesies of
something like a live body and that
these would couple very closely and that
would make some sense since your pose
would inform your view and vice versa
but there's another detail you need for
this to be an autonomous system an
adaptive agent which is um not just like
what's where is my body and what am i
seeing but where am i in space where do
i want to go
relative to the world and the various
things
that i believe are in the world how do i
pursue my goals in the world and so
enter uh the slam problem
um but
what's built with latent slam this is a
you know this is a very impressive
architecture um some details were
described below which you know
all these things governed by a singular
objective function
where the agent is able to
not just um uh make its way through the
world but also it's this powerful
self-supervised learning curriculum as
you're moving the two views views and
pose and landmarks each one providing a
source of predictions for the other
training up the other
um helping you to uh get a grip on the
world
uh
in terms of slam um two of the things
that um so this like broader notion of g
of g slam or generalized language this
would be a way of thinking of high level
cognition um i'm particularly interested
in uh
these two operations one's called
loop closure and the other is
graph relaxation no duplication i guess
that's three but the idea is um as to
mention when an agent finds itself in a
situation where its pose and view are
highly similar to something to what was
previously encountered uh this affords a
potentially unique opportunity you now
think you know where you are in space
and so this is a really good opportunity
to update your experience map and so
this
coming back around
it's not just a good opportunity in
terms of you have high confidence but it
creates a closed system so you closed a
loop
um
and so you basically have these
different equilibrium points in this
graph um which can be thought of as a
map also but basically because they're
all chained together um these are
sometimes modeled as like energetic
spring systems and they're all mutually
informing and constraining one another
and so when you find yourself with a
loop closure event where you you're in
this highly familiar state
you then take this as an opportunity to
refine your map and so you you know uh
will do a very fine if if you're within
a certain margin of error of um
a location
then if you think you're you really got
it
um
you'll then take the overall map and re
and relax and you'll basically
move around the various dependencies of
different nodes um in space the
different landmarks to adjust them and
have each one refine the other and form
the other however
if you're past some threshold for
similarity and it looks like you're
close but not quite there you're a
little bit different
uh
if you're surprised then you'll
duplicate the node and then you'll
create a new landmark and so now you'll
have a new graph and so this is
basically a kind of structure learning
and there's a lot of work in bayesian
cognitive science on um and within
active inference a lot of open work like
how do we effectively do
structure learning for handling complex
domains and
i'm suggesting and uh i think timothy um
hopefully would agree especially so
writing together uh would be that um
this provides a principled basis for
doing uh structural learning uh what's
interesting here though um in this
diagram that tim made
is that
as you're mapping out this warehouse
here
if you set these thresholds for uh
identifying a node differently if if
your graph relaxation no duplication
thresholds are set differently you get
very different models or maps you might
get very different structures or if you
will schemas or scripts
uh that's not the frame in terms of a
slam problem but the claim here is that
basically these the hippocampal uh
supposed place fields provide a basis
for
um
structure representations many of which
have resemblances the kinds of things
that were hoped for in like good
old-fashioned cognitive science
and a neurosymbolic ai um and so some of
and and part of what's hoped for is some
of the um aspects of potentially
uniquely human cognition high-level
cognition high level
um
are
require some sort of representational
scheme but if you set these parent but
if this is the mean by which you arrive
at representations and if these
parameters set differently could give
you um wildly different representations
these would have very different impacts
on the kinds of minds you might have
potentially including even things like
cognitive spectrums if you were to apply
this to a biological domain
and so there's some notion that for
instance you could even potentially
think of these parameters for the
hippocampal system um which are maybe
evolutionarily were originally
laid down as parameters for this for a
slam problem for an animal finding
itself in the world
but where
the continued operate in terms of um the
mechanisms of hippocampal and internal
plasticity
that
these if they're parameterized
differently in different people could
give you very different kinds of minds
and this potentially has very um
the significance of this might be
difficult to overstate in terms of
characterizing human difference these
might be some of the most important
variables
you could look at for saying how people
differ
in the way they relate to knowledge in
the world and not just so this would
have clinical consequences basic science
consequences maybe even
helping to explain some of uniquely
human cognition the kinds of things that
help to get um
symbolic uh
reasoning and like cumulative culture
off the ground
uh
there's other proposals that are kind of
similar to some mad dog
navigation perspective or slam
perspective
uh jeff hawkins out of numenta has a
proposal he calls a thousand brains
theory technically it should be called
something more like a hundred thousand
brains theory um where the idea is that
there's a common cortical algorithm
carried out by every single cortical
column
of doing this um object modeling and
navigation of the kindness described
with the kaplanatorinal system
um
i i find aspects of this to be
compelling but also very mixed feelings
and i can talk about that later with
anyone who's interested
uh there's another recent proposal in
this spirit by chris fields and michael
levin
where they're basically characterizing
morphogenesis as cells engaging in a
kind of way finding a navigation process
of where they ought to be
in this um synchronization manifold of
the phenotype and so they're all finding
their place you know singing as karma
might say like singing from the common
hem sheet knowing where they are but as
as they're synchronizing they're moving
around to find where they are this uh
unfolding geometric melody that
eventually becomes the phenotype of the
organism but the idea is that this
intelligence of wayfinding at the
cellular level
many of these mechanisms may have been
repurposed and recycled and deployed
differently for overt navigation and
that this is a frame for intelligence
more generally i found this to be
extremely compelling although what i'm
doing with this work is i'm focusing
more on the hippocampal enter rhino
system as a source of specific
adaptations with specific properties and
a major transition unit and evolution
potentially also of some connection to
things like um
ginsberg and jablanca's
major transition markers and unlimited
associated learning um they have a lot
of emphasis on hippocampal system and
its homologs there's very interesting
work that i'm only beginning to look
into in the insect
and insects with
the central complex and the mushroom
bodies and the way they handle
navigation i i think cross-referencing
the mammalian version and the insect
version would be really invaluable and
that's like that's a
a major to do that i'm hoping daniel
will help me with
so
uh
some other precedence would be in terms
of this idea of generalized navigation
that this would be a powerful frame for
understanding cognition uh comes from
some older work with hasabis and maguire
they found interestingly that
hippocampal patients not only are they
impaired in episodic
memory but they have trouble with
episodic imaginings of counter factuals
of novel situations and so they talked
about this construction system of the
spring this core system for memory and
imagining allowing for various forms of
um sophisticated modeling and creative
cognition and this seems to have been
part of what basically gave demis the
the confidence to go and found deep mind
and this is still a core aspect of what
they're doing there
and and the race is on for reverse
engineering the system and the race is
heating up and some really excellent
work would come from uh timothy barron's
group um i believe he's still at ucl um
they're showing like for instance uh
there's an architecture called the
tolman eichenbaum machine which i
strongly recommend checking out um
that's uh active inference compliant and
as a realization of the functioning type
of campus system they don't focus
as much on navigation although it can be
used for that and that's part of it that
the um
i'll come back in a second for the
differences here but um when in this
work one thing
of note is so
they're showing basically people
categorizing these stimuli um where you
have these birds with different length
necks and there's a kind of morpho space
in terms of characterizing the the
features and the various dimensions and
basically they're showing hippocampal
slash end to rhino-like representations
grid-like representations
um
being involved in helping to map out
this feature space and so this is one
example that's very commonly cited of
spatialized cognition or something that
might not seem clearly spatial but then
the idea of gsum would be once we've
spatialized it
then to what degree in our sense making
is it actually kind of navigation
through the space
and so this process of spatializing and
navigating through the space
simultaneously i would call that a slam
problem and i think a lot of cognition
can be fruitfully framed in this way and
i'm going to go a little further so
here's the tolman i can bomb machine and
he's showing like different um
i don't know is his face covered by the
thing i can't tell
uh well there he is
okay yeah so his work is unbelievable um
his group and um
but you know different things like uh
relations among people within uh
hierarchical um tree structures of their
relations uh doing things like
transitive inference of one property
related to another and a set of
dependencies but basically
using the hippocampal systems properties
to navigate navigate and manipulate
these spatialized representations
um there's other work from deep mind um
there's this other talk highly
recommended by um statchenfeld at all at
the main conference it's unbelievable
talk uh talking about the the recent
work from deepmind to reverse engineered
hippocampal systems uh
place cells and the grid cells of the
entourinal system as allowing for um
a variety of properties
um
some of
you know
very similar to baron's work and they
collaborate together
but one thing that's interesting about
this talk
is um
she makes a point that this isn't just
um for tasks that are like physical
space this isn't necessarily spatial um
i might uh
challenge that a bit um and and and say
that um we should basically always have
a prior of looking for the spatial
properties
of any task domain and then wondering to
what degree can we frame this as a slam
problem
and i think there's maybe two reasons of
doing for doing this
uh
one uh maybe three uh one is that um
basically putting things into a common
framework helps to
you to draw analogies across um
seemingly heterogeneous um domains and
this can be a source of insight in terms
of a common representational framework
um
for sense meaning sense making gives you
an ability to
have creative combinations from
seemingly different domains so
but the other reason is um
the hippocampal system like this was
specifically probably what it was
selected for this is a mapping system
for a animal foraging through value
through various spaces
and this isn't just evolutionary but
this is also developmentally and ongoing
this is an ongoing problem we have not
transcended this we are still in space
we still constantly have to move through
space and situate ourselves through
spaces physical spaces and also
conceptual spaces that's part of the
reason i'm really emphasizing the slam
framing because hippocampal system will
never lose this job description
and this the idea is that understanding
the ways in which is parameterized
specific operas operationalizations
i don't think that's a word
um
it's essential to keep in mind this
ecological significance and so this is
all within the spirit of um i guess a
broader view in cognitive science called
ecological rationality which is go back
to the origins
and try to understand it's tim bergen's
quote nothing in biology makes sense
except of the light of evolution take
that very seriously and run with it
um
one other thing that's uh so alongside
one thing i can get is connections one
thing a g slam perspective gets you is
connections to forging theory
and so um
you know if you're thinking of an animal
going through the world trying to
extract value
resources are often patchy and so as
you're moving through the world you uh
might be you know
balancing expiration and exploitation
with respect if you find a patch might
be good to exploit that for a bit if
it's particularly juicy but then as that
patch dries up maybe it's time to go
explore and then you want to move
between adaptively move between phases
of exploration exploitation staying
longer in some places and then moving to
other places and so these um jumps other
places like when a patch starts to dry
up and these are sometimes known as
levee flights and
this is playing actually into some of my
work in psychedelics and that um
informed by some really intriguing
suggestions from matt shine's group uh
the idea is that one of the mechanisms
impacted
by psychedelics might be um
potentially facilitating these kinds of
levy flights where you can think of more
creative cognition as involving more
exploration more broad associations
and there's all and
forging theory uh you know it's it's
extremely rich and well developed uh
there's all sorts of different modes of
foraging that could be thought of as
different modes of cognition there's
specific hypotheses and connections to
formalisms like the marginal value
theorem so you would have like a
hypothesis like when do you leave
well in the marginal value theorem that
is you leave a pact or when you when you
go and try to find the new you leave a
patch
when the average when your current
estimated value drops below what you
think the average rate of return should
be so this then you know gives you um
basically like you can now characterize
people where are they relative to these
different normative models
um and you know this idea
maybe has an even older vintage or maybe
you know newer relative evolution but
old relative to discourses in terms of
the art of memory and the art of memory
and the method of loci you know memory
especially before we wrote everything
down or when writing things out was
expensive
and even now to have something in your
mind where you know it could be at hand
where you can retrieve it to have like a
well-curated set of of knowledge it's
essential and so one of the best tricks
that were discovered is you actively
intentionally spatialize your knowledge
you actually create a physical place
that you visualize and you move through
it
and at each place you at each point in
this space you've placed different
things you want to remember
and part of the reason this likely works
so well like almost certainly is this is
um you know
the core of memory in the campus system
is actually involving a process of
um
it is a spatial mapper that's something
i would argue
uh there's connection to some other more
cognitive science i'm not going to get
into right now but like
multi-dimensional scaling where you
understand potentially complex domains
by mapping them onto a more a simpler
and potentially more
cognitively navigable space
and then
i'm not going to get into this right now
but um
actually i will so
real quick aside is with respect to
multi-dimensional scaling one of the
early things that got people excited for
about it was it's potentially used for
analogical reasoning or establishing
similarities between domains it's a very
important thing to know like how similar
is something relative to something else
like should these things be placed in
the same category or um
you know it's
and
one way of doing this was saying what is
the distance in this when you do
multi-dimensional scaling and you place
something in a feature space what is the
distance between these between different
things
and
the further apart the less similar they
are
but there are other models of analogical
reasoning and there's another race on to
try to figure out how we do analogical
reasoning and so some of these proposals
um you know they would go on beyond
something like um multi-dimensional
scaling but they involve specific
structure representations
but then we have a question what's the
ontological status of such things do
they actually exist in the minds we do
actually have representations or maybe
these things are more like they're
virtualized or inactively realized or
implicitly i suspect they probably we
probably um many of the the kinds of
structures you know
described in good old-fashioned
cognitive science might not be
biologically plausible but they might be
surprisingly biological plausible if you
actually have a system capable of
adaptively constructing graphs
based on um
your ability to extract value from these
graphs and situate things relative to
other things and so it's possible that
some of analogical reasoning and even
causal reasoning could be unlocked by
having a good means
of um
creating structured representations and
one of the things that the capital
system might seem to be able to do is
create these graphs where the different
place cells of the
campus can be thought of as nodes and so
if you duplicate a node you are now
basically doing structure learning um
you can you have you're complexifying
this uh representation
uh so this comes into my uh work in
other ways such as um models of
goal-oriented behavior i'm not gonna get
into too many details right now but here
would be the campus system and you see
um based on work of people like reddish
that
and also um like sam gershman has a
successor representation uh model but
basically you'll see these predictive
campuses a predictive map or what's
being predicted is
um where you'll see these sweeps of
activity that will proceed in front of
the animal before and then which will
predict which choice we'll do what arm
of a maze in my coda
and so
the idea is that the hippocampal system
is the top of the cortical hierarchy
and that any prediction errors that are
not handled elsewhere end up get
temporarily stored
in this volatile uh memory system which
is also
encoding these trajectories or these
series of equilibrium points of state
transitions
and that um basically you have
you know prediction areas
that are not handled elsewhere make
their way there get temporarily stored
and you can have um what's sometimes
called semantic pointer architecture
where basically
as you're moving as you're stepping
through these various equilibrium points
you can then unpack this as estimates of
system and world um in terms of
operative policies and actions and what
you expect at different points along
these different trajectories and so here
i'm focusing on moving through a
physical space in this case making tea
but this is i would argue this is also
part of what we do when we navigate
conceptual spaces that we are um
deciding what branches do we go down to
what degree where will we find what
kinds of value and that this is a
similar operation using similar
procedures from common neural processes
more recently i've been trying to extend
this to
models of
volition including um free will
and
let's see
i don't uh daniel how much time do i
have left i'm sorry
ten minutes okay great
so
this is uh less
i guess explicitly
slam framed um but still it's a
hippocampus at the center of it and so
so here
um
i'm trying to
this is a recent piece that's in
pre-print form which i would have uh i'd
love feedback on
but basically
the idea is as you're
that the present moment of experience
uh has a thickness to it
this is sometimes called the species
present or the remembered present
and that it seems to vary that the
minimal thickness of a moment of sense
making seems to be about a third of a
second and the upper bound seems to be
about three seconds
and that this seems to correspond to um
an epic so so you basically can so the
hippocampus system can whenever you
enter like a room
it'll tile that domain with a certain
degree of granularity it'll create these
hexagonal tilings of that space
and then within there that's where
you'll have these different attracting
attractors these different trajectories
play out orchestrating the rest of the
brain in terms of its dynamics to pursue
these various goals
and so the runway you have to work with
in terms of the the thickness of the
different rollouts for sophisticated
inference
would depend on
partially uh the shelf life
of this set of attractors before you
have to refresh them uh in some way
either set down an entirely new set or
um uh try to recreate the old one or
prevent the remapping and this would be
related to some of what was what was
just described with aerodynamics in
terms of how good of a grip do i have so
let's say you have like a poor grip on
what's happening and your prediction
error is going up this is not a good
situation for you
that might be a good opportunity to stop
hold and catch fire
re-tile space get a new set of operative
policies for sophisticated inference
and so
um
so here what i'm trying to do is show
that
um different levels of uh agonism of
these serotonergic receptors involved
with psychedelics um five hc2a receptors
are influencing the stability
of these sets of attractors
and
the
vividness with which you were doing
these imaginings and of rollouts of
actions into the future
and
here it's
it seems that what you could potentially
do is describe some of a dose response
curve for something like psychedelics
where as the dose increases
the extent of the rollouts
become greater you've stabilized them
and imagination become can become more
vivid and can influence your policy
selection more because you have more
confidence in what you're seeing and so
sophisticated inference your imaginings
are contributing more to your ongoing
overt action selection
up to a point
but then
and so this would be
and so this but then at a certain point
um the idea is you keep dosing uh the
animal or maybe the robot and it enters
more of a creative dreamlike regime
where it starts to lose coherence and
you see the the extent of these
rollouts of policy selection decreasing
uh things are becoming more vivid but
less coherent and sometimes you're
getting uh and this itself could
occasion error and potentially
re-gripping
in this model
and so the idea that is that this would
be a cognitive spectrum potentially in
addition to explaining some of the
neurophenomenology of things like
psychedelics this could potentially
explain some cognitive spectrums whether
we're talking about
maturation
or aging or
waking up you know when you first wake
up to going to sleep
these different parameterizations
of
your mechanisms for sophisticated
inference helping to basically provide a
neurophenomological handling of human
uh of what it's like to be a person and
all the variations of it
and so
i think
that should be it for right now and uh
happy to talk about all this with anyone
who's interested thank you
awesome thank you adam
hi daniel
hey
and you're muted
thank you very much any other uh notes
you'd like to add
um
i think that's uh i think that's it for
the moment great hope that you uh
consider anything and join us for the
round table shortly so thanks and we'll
be right back with the final
presentation by jf clutcher
all right we are back
this will be the final presentation of
this interval
this is jf klutcher
towards a symbolic implementation of
active inference for lego robots so
looking forward to hearing this and then
seeing you on the roundtable jf
i'm jean-francois and i will talk about
how i program lego robots as active
inference agents
this work contrasts with most robotic
implementations of active inference
which are based on probabilistic
inference so i hope this will spark some
interesting discussions
well first of all i'm a software
developer i'm not a neuroscientist
um
in my spare time well i like to code
models of cognition because i'm keenly
interested in all matters cognition and
consciousness
and i run them on robots because the
real world is hard and i believe that
writing code for robots is actually a
very good way to test my understanding
and
coding itself helps make abstract
concepts tangible to me
so what do i want to accomplish
well i want my robots to learn
autonomously while they conform to the
principles of active inference
this is the current version of my robots
there are two earlier versions and
there's one in early development
and here we'll see my uh robots the left
car to the right nd uh driven by the
interplay of generative models for
hunger danger avoidance and wanderlust
let's see them in action
they navigate his face
the sheet of paper on the floor
represents food
and they are attracted by the scent of
food simulated by an infrared beacon on
a pedestal
so cars making a beeline to the food
while andy is um
having a problem getting traction and
bumping into uh the walls
carl is cautiously approaching but we'll
get a little bit too close to the
pedestal
and this will engage its
danger
avoidance collision avoidance derivative
of models
he backs out
andy is observing all this
and he backs up as well
carl is reapproaching food
and this time we'll eat successfully
and he has noticed that carl was
freaking out
and in sympathy freaks out himself
while
carl is eating
all right so that was um
the robots as they are right now after
three iterations of this project
so what it take what does it take to
implement an active inference agent
well there are three approaches one um
let me take the numerical approach which
basically puts the mathematics of active
inference into code and
runs uh that on robots
um another approach is to take a
symbolic approach
where
we have a
code functions that operate mostly on
symbols predicates etc here we can see
we have the symbols for hungary very
danger curiosity etc
um but that's not the only option
take e coli e coli is an active
inference agent and its implementation
is biochemical well i clearly didn't
take that route i went this symbolic
route
well mostly because it's the familiar
one to me and it provides me with a
better scaffolding for my intuitions and
exploration i also find that
it handles complexity quite well
when i started this project in 2017
my first thoughts uh were to implement a
society of mind i'd come across this
concept uh
decades ago it's a theory of mind put
forward by marvin minsky
50 years ago
and
at its core it says that intelligent
behavior emerges from
a lot of simple actors that interact in
simple ways
it so happens that i look at it as an
architectural principle as well
so how does one implement a society of
mind um
well
to me the answer is clear is we use the
actor model
the actor model is a model of concurrent
computation that was introduced by carl
ewit in 1973.
according to this
model of computation
we have
independent actors which are
processes concurrent processes each one
managing its own state and the only way
a
an actor can interact or influence
another actor is by sending it messages
and once an actor receives a message it
will interpret that message possibly
modify its internal state and as a
consequence of fire messages to other
actors
so building a society of mind using the
actor model is quite a natural fit
i also happen to program in the elixir
language and elixir is a
message-oriented multi-process language
which is based on the actor model so
it's a it's a perfect fit
so here we are it's 2017.
i own two um lego mindstorms ev3 kits
they're wonderful robotic skids with a
a nice choice of sensors mini motors and
a
computer the ev3 brick that controls
them all
and i want to build a society of mind in
elixir on my eb3 robots
i'm in luck there's a linux distribution
called eb3dev
that allows me to run elixir on
the ev3 brick so i'm all set
so
that start that allowed me to start this
project and this project as i said has
completed three iterations and i'm
starting a fourth one
and we look at each one in turn
reviewing the goals and also the issues
uncovered
first iteration 2017 version one a
simple society of mind as i call it
so
i implement a an ad hoc model cognition
it's not something that i i took from
research is something i i
made up myself it's homebrewed and let's
have a quick tour
so being a society of mine is bucketed
with uh
actors
and um
we have the detector actors and their
responsibilities
are to
interface with the sensors and to pull
them
periodically to generate
percepts which are events
that are
like all other events that the actors
will produce are sent to the central
nervous system actor which is a
dispatcher which will then
dispatch these events to other actors
that are interested in them
there's a memory actor and all events uh
are sent to the memory as well to be
stored for a certain amount of time and
represent the past if you want to the
agent and
the other actors are able to query this
memory in order to make whatever
decisions they need to make
one of the key actors are the preceptor
actors
and what they do is they
ingest
events perceptive ants
originally from the detectors
and analyze them maybe in the context of
the past and produce higher level
percepts for example a preceptor might
be digesting a distance a percent from a
detector
look at it and say
ah given
prior
distances
i'm getting closer to an obstacle and in
a higher level uh and then produce that
percept and the high level perceptor
might say ah i am
getting closer to an obstacle and i am
perfectly close to it so uh
producer percent that says collision
imminent and so forth and so on
another important part of actor is the
motivator and motivator is responsible
for deciding what the robot needs what
the robot wants and it expresses this
need or this want as a motive
event that is again centered in central
nervous system dispatched in this case
uh to the behavior actor and the
behavior actor then takes this motive
and acts on it by emitting
intent events
that are
listened to by the actuator actors
who translate these intents into actual
commands and move the robot
one key point is that the motivators
actually are compete with one another so
that the most important need of the
robot is the one that's expressed so for
example
being getting getting to safety is more
important than uh um satisfying hunger
there's um
let's look a little bit into one of the
types of actors the behavior actors and
uh the behavior actor is actually quite
complex it does a lot of work it's not a
simple actor it's implemented as a state
machine and with every state transition
triggered by a new percepts
intents are emitted and so we can have a
uh
a behavior actor which job is to uh
direct the uh robot to the food
so um it works so let's see nd version
one
moving about and trying to get the boot
which in this case is the blue paper on
the ground
[Music]
so though it tries to avoid collisions
uh it not always succeed here it finds
out it's stuck
backs out
goes around
doing a better job at avoiding obstacles
and now makes a beeline to the food
having detected it
approaches
cautiously and
feeds
all right
so this worked quite well but there were
issues with this version one uh not this
is i don't think it was visible in the
video but the robot was frequently
overwhelmed by a constant flow of
percepts out of the receptor the
detectors constantly feed percepts into
the society of mind and after a while
they kind of back up and the robot
starts reacting to
uh
old events
and one solution was to actually put the
robot to sleep once in a while paralyze
it let the events wash through the
system and then wake it up with uh with
a clean slate so that was kind of a
little bit awkward and another issue was
that well there's no learning going on
the robot doesn't get better with each
run and given the model it wasn't clear
to me where i could fit uh learning in
there so
time for uh version two
so i need to find a way to make my
robots learn
and they also need to um
better focus and
be able of attention so they can avoid
being overwhelmed with all these
unneeded sensations
i also need more computing power so i
replace the eb3 brick by a raspberry pi
3.
about the same time i come across andy
clark's book surfing uncertainty and i
find that the predictive brain makes
quite a lot of sense to me
i think it tells a really good story
about learning and attention so i
decided to implement a predictive
society of mind
this is my first crack at it i won't go
into uh the details i do in a companion
paper
um let's just say that they are actors
for managing beliefs validating them
making predictions and taking action
when um to make these predictions come
true
there's also an attention actor for
turning detectors on and off as needed
and a focus actor for prioritizing
belief validation
i do introduce some learning the robot
learns what actions tolerate correlate
well with success but that's about it
and
there's the the model does not feel
quite right to me at this point and they
are bottleneck actors for example
there's only one experienced actor
there's only one attention actor only
one memory of course and only one focus
and
in a society of mine that just doesn't
feel right
yep it still it works
and let's watch andy um at on its first
run it's nd version two hasn't learned
anything yet
so the same scenario
so andy has detected the food would like
to move towards it but doesn't know
which actions validate believed
best
it smells food but still you know it's
just heading into the wall
so for indeed
it's been quite uh
unproductive here in its quest for food
it's a little bit painful to watch let's
stop
um now here's andy uh 30 runs later and
it's much more competent
about matching beliefs and actions
smells food and
very confidently makes a bee line
to that food
just
here we go
slowly approaching
obviously a very different anti from the
the naive one
and there we go
okay so it worked
uh but there's still uh there were
issues with version two first the model
doesn't quite feel right um to me it
just doesn't quite capture um
something didn't i didn't feel right
about it and they were model bottleneck
actors as well which is not a good sign
and learning was limited to action
selection
so time for version three
i call this one a society of generative
models
so i go back to the andy clark's book
and uh and also read on the free energy
principle
um and it becomes clear to me that
generative models are actually quite
central in fact it's
generate models all the way down so i
get to work
on a new model
in this new model i have very few kinds
of actors they're
detector actors as before to interface
with the sensors
actuator actors to interface with motor
speakers and whatnot
and the only other kind of actor are the
generative model actors the gm actors
and there's quite a few of them in this
case here uh 16 and
they do the heavy lifting they do the
belief updating the predicting the
raising prediction errors the selecting
selection of actions and
they are responsible for remembering
their past states and and actions
um each gm operates within its science
scope there there's one for uh locating
food one for avoiding obstacles one for
a detecting approach to obstacles and so
forth and so on
the gm actors have parent-child
relationships
um
a
apparent gm sends predictions as events
about what it expects its children gm's
to believe even what it itself
believes and these prediction errors
these predictions flow downward
and
prediction errors flow upward if a child
gm receives a prediction about what it's
supposed to believe or it's expected to
believe and it's not what it believes
and it sends back a prediction error up
to its parents
um
well that means that a uh generic
model's perceptions are
in fact the uncontested predictions it
makes plus the prediction errors it
receives and the gm updates its beliefs
based on these perceptions
and given what it believes it may decide
to take some actions and then raise
intent events that reach the actuators a
little bit like before
the generative models are kind of
grouped uh into different areas of
concern there was uh there's being which
is responsible for
deciding whether we're in danger we're
hungry or free there are the danger uh
gms which have to do with uh
clearing obstacles uh trying to stay in
well-lit areas avoiding collisions with
other the other robot and whatnot
then there are hunger gms
um that have to do with eating seeking
food etc
and there's the freedom gm which i call
the wonderlust gm which basically
says well i'm neither endangered nor
hungry so let me just roam around
and finally there are these two ones
here which have to do with guessing the
intent of the other robot and we'll go
into more details with these two
so let's look more closely at the gm
actor remember that a gm as a as parent
gms and
child gms
that the predictions flow downward and
prediction errors flow upwards
let's look inside
a gm defines one or more conjectures um
a conjecture is a potential belief
for example whether i know where food is
or whether i'm about to collide i have
two different conjectural beliefs
a belief may either be a goal that's a
belief we want to make true like i'm
eating or an opinion which is a belief
that i want to validate for example that
i am
approaching food
a conjecture is typically activated when
the gm receives a prediction about the
conjectured belief
and a conjecture knows how to check its
associated belief to see if it's valid
it knows how to make predictions given
that belief and how to decide what
actions to take to either achieve or
test the belief
a gm learns how well alternate courses
of actions policies correlate to
achieving validating belief
it also
keeps track of which child gm it trusts
more should they send competing
prediction errors so it does precision
weighing
um
and each gm actor
works in its own time it's a concurrent
process
and it does
one
uh
it does it it operates one round at a
time and we'll see what a round means
and it remembers um it's fast rounds
uh it's past perceptions the predictions
is received in the past its past beliefs
and actions
so now let's look at the uh life cycle
of a gm actor
well as i said agm actor operates round
after round after round so what's around
first the window round is started
gm carries over the perceptions and uh
beliefs from the previous round it
doesn't start from from scratch
and if it's in the midst of trying to
achieve a gold belief it may
at us as it starts you around activate
conjectures for that
action belief
and um as a result
send
predictions to child gms
once we're done starting the round is
active and then the uh gm actor just
sits there for maybe i don't know 300
milliseconds waiting for events
events like predictions coming from
above from parents that will then
activate uh conjectures trying to prove
that the predicted belief is actually uh
true this will cause predictions to be
sent to child gms
and as a consequence maybe
prediction errors will come up and the
gm will update its perceptions
when the the round is completed either
because we've heard from all the
children or because time's up
the gm completes this current round it
updates uh position weighing keeps its
trusted perceptions updates its beliefs
uh as a result may send prediction
errors because they could the new
beliefs conflict with uh predictions
that it had received uh before
it updates its policies
and um
it decides on the course of action since
uh intense and notifies the round it's
completed and we continue so round after
round after round
i mentioned that uh
there were two very uh kind of more
interesting gms in the society of uh
generative models
these are these two gm's and they
represent uh my little foray into theory
of mind these gms
are dedicated to guessing what the other
robot is doing
so each robot observes the other
and detects patterns of movements and
infra intentions
from these patterns
there's only two kinds of intents that
are
inferred one is that the
other robot is has detected food and is
making a move towards the food or that
the other robot is
in danger and hispanic
now how does a robot see the other robot
well
in addition to the
array of sensors i already had from
previous version i've added
a new sensor a 360 beacon seeker and
what this beacon seeker sees is the
beacon um on the back of
the other robot so each robot has a
beacon on its back that broadcast and
then 360 radia
radius
circumference angle
it
signifies here i am here i am here i am
and the other robot can
detect how far the other robot is and at
which relative orientation
so
that let's say one robot here uh carl is
making a bee line to the food
andy has been observing this
and seeing the pattern of movement which
is a very uh straight uh
uh
trajectory
uh infers that the carl has detected
food and is homing in on it and may
decide to follow carl and get to the
food as well
um
another pattern of movements would be a
chaotic
pattern of movement and i'd say
carl had been backing away in panic from
hitting the pedestal and andy was
observing this and it noticed that this
thing kind of a chaotic pattern and
inferred that
a car was in a panic and decided to get
into panic as well if you remember the
video at the beginning of the
presentation
so
this is doing well
but um
we all know debugging is hard i find out
also that debugging societies of mind on
robots is very hard
in order to help myself i develop a
simulated simulation environment i think
of it as simulated embodiment which
allows me to
observe what goes on inside a given
robot
it helps for debugging it helps for
experimentation
in the simulation word world
a robot
my robots
virtual robots live in a grid world
there are obstacles the blue tiles there
are uh kind of darker areas that the
robot tries to avoid which are
represented in the black and gray uh
squares
and and then there's the food um which
is the green uh tiles here
as the robots uh
navigate that space you know by using
their uh society of generative models
i can see where each robot is in terms
of its state
first i can see where it's located i can
see its orientation when it's last said
what the last action it executed and i
can see the state of its virtual sensors
and virtual actuators
i can also peek inside
the various generative models of a robot
here i'm looking into the avoiding
obstacle gm of nd and i can look at the
state in the current round or in past
rounds and i can see which predictions
came in which conjectures are activated
what are the current perceptions
uh what beliefs that the robot uh holds
at the time and um what actions
it thinks are uh
are more likely to work and what actions
it is taking
very very helpful but this moves really
fast and so i i can actually slow down
the simulation even pause it and then
look inside the various generative
models and see if what's happening is
what i expected would happen so create
debugging debugging tool and
experimentation tool
so i'm quite happy with version three i
think it aligns quite well with the
active inference ontology
um there are no bottleneck actors
and but learning is still limited to
selecting um
action policies
however i think that the version 3 sets
the stage very well for the new
iteration and this one has an ambitious
learning agenda and it's just getting
started
so version 4 starting now
i call it active inferencing
so here's what i want to achieve as the
robot interacts with its environment and
i and learns how to maintain
it i wanted to learn how
i want it for i want for it to learn how
to maintain its homeostasis
by uh growing uh its own society of
generative models so instead of being
given
an apiary set of generative models i
want the robot to learn that set
not only that but i want each gm to
learn its own capabilities i wanted to
infer its logic programs that when
executed will infer predictions from
perceptions will infer beliefs
from uh also from its perceptions
and infer policies that will validate or
invalidate its belief
so how does one do that
well there's a very very interesting
paper that i
found which is uh called making sense of
sensory input written by richard evans
and all from a deep mind
and
it answers the question of how do you uh
learn
um a
causal theory
that
explains a sequence of sensations
and once you've built that causal theory
you can then apply it to predict what
the next round of sensations or
perceptions will be and thus make
predictions about them
now just to to read from the beginning
of the paper
making sense involves constructing a
symbolic causal theory that both
explains the sensory sequence and also
satisfies a set of unity conditions
now unity conditions are actually a set
of constraints derived from cons
philosophy
um
that ensure that all the pieces of the
theory form a coherent whole
semantically speaking i won't go into
the details but it's quite fascinating
the paper goes on
making sense of sensory input is a type
of program synthesis but it is
unsupervised program synthesis
so the the paper
presents an app reception engine
this is the software that will generate
will infer causal theories from sensory
data
it is
at its core it's a code generator what
it does is it synthesizes logic programs
that implement these causal theories
and when you run these logic programs
you can predict incoming sensations so
essentially a perception engine
generates uh predictors
and the way it does that is it searches
for predictor logic programs in a space
of potential possible logic programs
it's a search problem and
it's it's the the search space is
extremely large of course so we need a
way to constrain it
we need to apply
sorry strong inductive biases to
restrict the search
that's where the unity conditions come
in
so
in order to
derive its own predictor a gm will
search for good predictors using app
perception
so given around a prior round of
perceptions remember that the uh
the gm has a memory of each round and in
each round a set of simultaneous
perceptions given that sequence
a gm will search a space of candidate
predictors for a good one
what makes a predictor well two things
first there's a scope and then there's
rules the scope is
essentially the objects the rules will
be about and the belief predicates that
will be used in the rules
the rules well there's three kind of
rules there's the static rules
which
apply on a set of simultaneous
perceptions like at time n uh in it the
rules validate and possibly also infer
uh implied perceptions missing
perceptions
an example of a static rule might be
if
the robot is at distance zero from an
obstacle it is also touching the
obstacle
then there are causal rules and the
causal rules
essentially
infer the perceptions at time n
plus one given the perceptions at time n
uh
they predict the next perceptions
an example of a causal rule would be
if the robot is at distance x from an
obstacle and the robot is approaching
the obstacle
in the next round of perception the
distance of the robot to the obstacle
should be smaller
and finally there are conceptual rules
which are rules that kind of make the
whole predictor hang together
semantically there are
rules of mutual exclusion for example
there can only be one distance between a
robot and an obstacle
and rules of uniqueness
which
i'm sorry the rule of uniqueness would
be that they they can only be one
distance yes rule of uniqueness they can
only be one distance for example between
two objects and mutual exclusion might
be um a robot
cannot both
approach an obstacle and be touching it
at the same time
so the
app reception engine of uh will kick in
for agm
when the current predictor of the gm is
no longer good enough for the jobs like
we've
we've produced a predictor and now we
have more rounds of perceptions and the
predictor is doing a really bad job at
uh predicting the next perceptions and
then the perception engine will kick in
and try to produce a better predictor
for that gm so that happens for all the
gms
and once we have a good predictor the gm
even the current set of perceptions can
infer the next set of perceptions thus
make predictions
so we talked about uh how a gm learns um
but what about how it learns how about
learning uh the entire society of gm's
how does a robot
form its society of gms through
interactions with the world
well
this was going to be guided by a uh
a midtech cognition gm that's something
that's given when the robot starts live
it has a basic set of
detectors set of actuators that is a
given and it also has a metacognition
gm it's also a given
the
metacognition gm
its role is to watch over and guide the
evolution of a society of gms
that's the action
for it to function though each gm must
act as a
cogniti cognitive sensor
it must
produce sensations
such that
such as um are prediction errors
trending up or down
uh do policies
uh particularly uh predictably impact uh
my beliefs
or
very importantly within my purview is
the robot's homeostasis at risks these
are cognitive sensations that a gm will
produce will be uh
absorb uh listened to by the
metacognition gm
and
that will allow it to update its own
beliefs about
how well the society of gms is doing uh
does it have sufficient coverage is each
gm capable enough and based on that um
may take corrective actions by creating
new gms
and
possibly if one gm is not doing very
well that is stuck in a rut um
removing it and replacing it with
another so that's the the role of the
metacognition energy
so
how can the robot tell whether it's
doing better or worse than before given
what it has learned well
feelings
that's how
so a robot will have internal sensors
for feelings and i'm thinking about
feelings of hunger
which increases uh with physical and
mental exertion and
is reduced with eating
there's the feeling of pain which would
go up with the number of collisions but
would be reduced automatically with the
passage of time simulating healing and
then i'm thinking also
of the feeling of only
which
goes up is if a gm is not learning
anything if it's logic programs are
unchanged for a long period of time and
but on me goes away when the
the gm is learning
feelings uh i have a balance
positive negative i'm hungry very hungry
negative balance i'm not hungry at all
positive balance
and a negative balance signals uh risks
to homeostasis
and uh
when uh beliefs are derived from um
feelings with a negative balance or a
positive balance then these beliefs take
on this balance
and
this is going to be used to uh
prioritize actions because actions that
promote beliefs with a strong
[Music]
balance
will be prioritized for
actions that do not so uh in other words
a a agm with very strong feelings will
have its actions
prioritized over uh gm's that currently
uh want to take action but from uh
you know less
less uh
less feelings
less powerful feelings and if these
actions um
uh conflict then the actions of the
the the gm with stronger feelings will
uh predominate will take over
well given all this what do i think
makes a robot an active entrance robot
well there's many things but i'd like to
think that it's
in its simplest expression for me at
well
at least um an active
uh robot is one that learns what to do
in order to feel good uh more often than
not
so i'm hoping that this uh
work will raise some uh big questions
and and give me some insights into them
uh for example what is the appraised
knowledge that an agent must possess to
learn autonomously
what makes unsupervised learning
converge on competency diverge and maybe
a little bit more far out what can
growing a society of gms learn from
developmental biology i
suspect that there are principles at
work here that
both that they both share
so that's it thank you very much thank
you to the active inference institute
for their help and encouragement
um the version three of uh my work is
available on github it's open source i
can be reached on discord and by email
and the companion paper to this talk is
available on senator
all right great talk jf we'll take a
quick break
and we'll be right back with the round
table
all right we are back
this is the beginning of the second
round table that's our last session in
the second interval of the second
applied active inference symposium
and some more may be joining
but i am joined here by adam saffron
bruno lara and jakobs mecca
and
maybe just to begin it would be awesome
if anybody who
wanted to do
thank you
and welcome to jf
carl will be joining shortly
um so perhaps to begin
if anybody would like to
provide a reflection on a talk that was
not their own
what was something that you felt like
was brought to the table
what was a a key problem area that was
addressed and how did you see active
inference being implemented and
adding meaning in that situation
i can maybe uh quickly just
comment on uh
jf's presentation since
was the most recent i think uh
definitely this symbolic approach to
active inference is one that is
has perhaps not been
um
that pushed forward
in and
like obviously there are different um
approaches all around the field but i
feel like that this particular
perspective on pursuing this kind of
emergent
generative models which only have the
very basic um
kind of setup but then the complexity
[Music]
emerges through the usage of elixir and
prologue
i think was really interesting
and um
yeah i mean we
talked about js project
in the
organizational meeting units quite a lot
but
every time i think about it it's
really cool to
see this implementation
no
i mean in terms of the
recent one just
the app reception engine like the
content inspiration and i found that to
be really exciting
um especially because you know uh
i've been taking some inspiration from
kant some of the work and like wondering
whether basically
like these categories like are they not
just like preconditions for judgment but
like any kind of sense making whatsoever
like any sort of
world with composition that could be
navigated and parsed
and so
um to see that that kind of work was
being done with that level of
sophistication was just amazing
it is a thread that came up multiple
times with juxtaposing discrete time
continuous time and all of these
and then it's almost like another
dialectic with the numerical and this
the distributional approach
to
variational inference sampling message
passing a whole taxonomy of approaches
that we've seen
for active inference models and also
models of perception cognition and
control outside of active inference
and so
maybe
jf if you wanted just to provide
a
a thought on where you see the symbolic
perspective coming from
and intertwining with active inference
directions and robotics like we were
talking about today
well i i think it comes in
from different uh uh perspective ones is
explainability
of of uh choices and behaviors
if uh the um
the the robot is driven by a
symbolic reasoning
then it becomes relatively
straightforward
for
it to provide an explanation of its
behavior in terms of the chain of
reasoning
that led to it so that's that's of
interest
uh in and of itself
the other aspect is uh when it comes to
the app perception engine
it has a
an ability
to develop a causal uh theory a symbolic
causal theory from relatively
small
data set
so unlike machine learning
solutions which require
intensive uh
intensive learning process which
leads to an
obscure
uh
causal theory if you want uh with the
appreciation engine you have a
relatively small amount of data that
that as input and a a causal theory
that's
symbolically expressed
as output which can serve as a basis for
explanation and justification and
rationale
that being said
uh if the um
as part of the uh
process of perception
uh gm uh uh abduces latent objects and
and induces uh predicates
uh the meaning of these predicates are
uh only uh
to be inferred in context because
they're gonna be called like p1 and p2
and object o1 object o2
you may by examine emanation just maybe
infer ah i think that
we're looking at a predicate that has to
do with uh navigation and and and
avoidance but that will not be clear so
i i think uh
in that regard there there are gains but
they're not they're not absolutely clear
in terms of
explainability
but when it comes to active inference i
think
that
what matters
to me
is that the robots behave
according to the principle of active
inference and not necessarily by
implementing the mathematics of it
so i don't think it's a contradiction
as far as i'm concerned these are four
diseases that
are our mind just symbolic programming
and that's why i'm doing it that way
thank you it's almost like in the
textbook
of active inference where we have the
high and the low road and here's like
the symbolic airdrop
actually arriving at a similar
place
although being
quite disjoint in its origins from the
particular partition
flows on continuous numerical variables
a lot of the ways that we've seen things
develop in the past several years
so
welcome
carl if you would like to
say hello or provide any remarks on
anything that you've seen at the
symposium or any overview thoughts on
active inference and robotics
well i've greatly enjoyed all the
presentations there's so many different
perspectives so uh um
i will i would imagine
my comments will fall on from what
people want to talk about so i'm going
to just pick up on that last theme so
you know that
jean france was um symbolic dropping on
from high
i i thought it was a really intriguing
perspective um and it's a perspective
that i've been actually forced into in
certain applications of the uh golo
fashioned mathematics of active
inference so i thought it'd be useful to
share that um
in the sense that
when you
write down
discrete state space models and use the
maths of uh minimizing variational
expected free energy
to invert those models
very often you're confronted
with specifying those models with
boolean logic you know if this then that
um and um you know
literally in the code which you write to
specify a particular tensor that maps
from some causes to some consequences
you are literally using if and then
statements and and or statements in
order to generate the tensors or or
or the um
the matrices that sort of encode
probabilistic mappings which now become
um
deterministic mappings simply because
you're populating these tensors with
zeros and zeros and ones so i do see an
enormous
opportunity here to actually um bring
together
the um you know
the mathematics and the simple
probability theory just using you know
um categorical distributions or
dirichlet distributions of a particular
sort you know where
you're only dealing with some zeros and
one probabilities and the kind of logic
uh
and perception that you were talking
about i thought that was absolutely
fascinating and one one thing that
intrigues me
is
if you can do that
um
then that there is um
a way of doing your searches of all
the
potential programs or logical um
statements that are internally
consistent
um with the evidence at hand you know
for example i could build a generative
model where i can be in two places at
the same time or two things can be in
the same place at any one time that's
you know from the point of the genitive
model i can write that down
without an exclusion principle
um but when i now come to see who asks
the question is that model relative to
another model that can be written down
in terms of boolean logic
that precludes two things being in the
same place any one time
does that simpler model now provide a
more a better explanation for the
evidence at hand
so technically what that means is that i
can apply the rules of bayesian model
selection
to this model versus that model where
the model just is a statement of
propositions uh
logical propositions um and there are
ways of um there are ways of sort of
automating that very efficiently called
bayesian model reduction
um
and i'm just wondering whether you could
take a lot of pressure off the search
for
the internally consistent
logical structures that you're dealing
with and if you can cast it in terms of
um
in terms of bayesian model reduction
which quite simply is measuring the
evidence the probability of this
sequence of outcomes that can itself be
categorical you know i'm in this state
all that state
the probability of that particular
sequence of discrete outcomes given this
structure this generative model that is
articulated as a logic and if you can do
that i think that'd be very very
powerful because that speaks to a common
theme which i think
most of us or you were talking about
which is this issue of structure
learning um you know and what you're
talking about is is sort of a principled
way to get the right parsimonious
structures that have this
you know this coherence i can't remember
you
you were even taking it right back to
sort of 19th century philosophy or 18th
century philosophy in terms of in the
constraints would be really great
to see
whether that kind of um
sort of logical structure uh the
philosophers like um
actually could be discovered or
disclosed just using uh good
old-fashioned basic model selection that
there seems to be a close symmology
there with some of the work of people
like josh tenenbaum where he's he's he
certainly articulates structurally
learning from the point of view of
radical constructivism using sort of
programmed searches and sort of um
um
you know casting generative models as
programs and then it's trying to score
the quality of these programs uh using a
form of basic model selection and he
claims to be able to do sort of millions
um very very effectively with it within
um you know within a few seconds
have you have you looked at josh
chellenbaum's work at all
not yet but i certainly will
and i just want to uh make clear that
that the appreciation engine uh was
developed by richard evans uh in the
paper making sense of sensory input
um and and yes one of the the the core
issues is inductive bias uh how do you
restrict the search space so that you
can have a chance of finding within a
reasonable amount of time a logic
program that is a competent
predictor
and those and that's where cons
synthetic unity of our perception
uh plays in
as it provides constraints on the the
class of uh logic programs which are uh
acceptable
uh
which are are yeah which are uh
considered valid
and
if if i make a contribution because this
is work in progress
i would like to add additional
constraints of from the fact that we do
not uh we're not trying to generate
one generative model in in
in and of itself but as in the context
of a society of generative models so
general will
borrow
its perception domain from the belief
domain of other generative models thus
creating additional constraints and as
it searches it will try not to modify
its scope in such a way that it orphans
other generative models so
as the
society of general models grows so does
the same set of constraints that apply
on reducing
the search for a
predictor in any of the generative
models themselves so i'm hoping that as
the society of general models grows so
does the set of constraints that apply
on the searches for any one of them but
i think the name of the game is very
much in
this
the richness and the strength of the
inductive biases that are applied on
search
just to
highlight a few pieces of what were
addressed and then to bruno or adam or
anyone who'd like to add
it impressed on me robotics is radical
constructivism
not just in the sense of the
constructing models but also in the way
that adam described in terms of the
relationship to the embodied artifact so
that is one interesting piece and
another
in this
quest to find the rainbow that connects
first principles and analytic
formulations
through mesoscale for example
computational code all the way to the
last mile in the cases that we heard
from one hot chen in the previous
session
carl when you described the way that
boolean logic
enters at the level of execution
was very interesting
and suggests that there is kind of like
a uh a brackish area similar to that
between discrete and continuous time
models in like hierarchical modeling but
here
where
the numerical and the
statistical approaches to active
inference
are
becoming connected to
actual logical implementations and
design choices that have to do with
which functions are executed first or
the conditions that certain things occur
in
and so there actually is a meeting
ground or an interface in a way
implicitly already and so it is very
interesting to see how
jf's work on the generative model
generation
process
is now approaching that intersection
from the other side and suggesting it's
like if you see a car coming from the
other direction
there's a road
and now this high and low road network
starts to grow more pathways
so
bruno or adam would be happy to hear any
thoughts you have
um yeah thanks um
yeah i mean i think that's that's um
that's much our case as i was telling
you like we come from this other side of
of the story
and at the end we have to make some
choices on implementations
and so far we've been very focused on on
these um self-organizing maps most of
our work is on that
uh and that's actually one one of the
questions i have for for all of you like
what's your take on on all these
approaches that we're trying to like
we're coming from a different field from
a different
point of view and in a way we are almost
uh intentionally avoiding
uh probabilistic approaches to active
inference no
so
i don't know what's what's your opinion
on that that was the first one and the
second one is more like a um i don't
know like a a doubt
a question for carl like
what do you see in the near future on on
all these things so that we're working
on on prediction aerodynamics and this
monitoring of the of the error over time
um
can yeah i think that's that's
i'd i'd love to speak to that if i can
yeah
in fact interestingly it does actually
also speak to your question daniel i
just wanted to point out also that this
notion of moving between continuous
states-based models and discretized
state-space models is something that
people in quantum computing and physics
are going to keep their close eye on
because if you get all digital um then
the opportunity for quantum computing
raised it raised its head so it was also
very pragmatic
um uh pragmatic reason to sort of
look at that um that transition and also
just to bring in uh adam's point you
know not only um was he suggesting that
we quantize discretize
spatialize in terms of little tiles and
places uh receptive fields for being
here as opposed to being over there but
he's also suggesting we do that in time
so i think the quantitization
of space time in a generative model
is a really important thing of course
you know you could argue that that's a
step closer to good old-fashioned
symbolic ai
that has a meaning in in the sort of
focus psychology sense
so to come to bruno's question so the
big divide here is between um from my
point of view at least degenerative
models that are of continuous states and
time versus genetic models that are of
discrete states and
states and time and clearly you need
both yeah in the sense the the world
that a roboticist and indeed me and my
children live in is a continuous world i
have to move around it i have to um
control continuous temperatures and all
sorts of things and
and yet it seems as if the the
intelligence is at a symbolic level so i
think what we're talking about is a
hybrid genetic model and then the
question is how do you get the sort of
discrete parts to talk to the continuous
parts but if we just focus on the
continuous parts um and just to answer
bruno's question directly um
first of all what i'm saying is you
can't ignore the continuous bits so
everything you would talk about in terms
of self-organizing maps has to be there
at some level um it's just a question of
whether you can put a more symbolic um
logical structure on top of it to cause
screening sufficiently to resolve all
the complexity um the i i i loved you
your work um
i could see uh all the important um
issues in terms of um
representing uncertainty as
the if you like
the stand-in for the valence of how i am
doing so i was amused to hear that
you're trying you're actively avoiding
probability theory yet for me everything
you said was all about probability it's
all about uncertainty and that was at
true at so many levels so just to answer
danielle's question to you uh the
relationship between free and
variational free energy and the
prediction error is really trivial and
very simple it's just under continuous
state space models with gaussian random
fluctuations
the uh free energy gradients are just
are the prediction errors the signed
prediction errors so it's really your
simple quadratic forms for the log
probabilities um so um self-organizing
maps that organize themselves in terms
of responding to prediction errors just
are systems that are performing a great
inflow on a variation free energy under
the assumption you're dealing with
continuous states that have gaussian by
random by central limit theorem uh
gaussian random fluctuations so i i you
know that that's all exactly what you
know
what would please me if i was if i was a
probabilistic
committed to the probabilistic
punishment
you your i think your thing you're
bringing to the table though is is this
sort of the dynamics of the uncertainty
or the amplitude the prediction error
the unsigned prediction error the sort
of the behavior of prediction errors
over you know with the separation of
time scales and i think that that that's
a really important um really important
move um
i i see slight homologs of that not
formally identical but certainly um
homologs of that um
um from the point of view of an engineer
this would be like getting the kalman
gain right you know if you interpret a
calm and gain on a kalman filter as
assigning the right precision or
confidence to the
prediction errors as they come in
relative to to the state estimators and
your your prior beliefs that you've
accumulated getting that right having an
adaptive kalman filter where you're
actually optimizing the calm and gain uh
you know
that would be if you like the state of
the art hierarchical camera bc filtering
so that if i was a psychiatrist i would
say this is exactly what goes wrong in
people with uh schizophrenia and autism
is that they've got their estimators of
the overall
um
uncertainty or prediction error wrong um
and that they now need to um you know
and this is an explanation for um
false belief updating of false state
estimation from the common filtering
point of view
the the other point um that struck me in
in in the early part of your talk was um
something which um
as a neurobiologist or motor control
theorist um
something that they would find very
entertaining which was the
link between
the ability to ignore stuff and sensory
attenuation i don't know if you've come
across that in robotics but
um
certainly in terms of motor control of
the kind i think you're using which is
which i would um ascribe to the
equilibrium point hypothesis like
approach approaching so you you're
putting your set point into into the
actuator and you're letting the reflexes
do the rest but
you've got to control carefully um how
those prediction errors are used to
drive the actuator make sure they don't
come back up and change your state
estimation and so from the point of view
of sensory attenuation that just is
attenuating the precision or the inverse
variance or estimation of the overall
amplitude
so and finally you know
looking at the long term trends
in the estimated precision i think is
you know it is a really important way
to see whether you've got the right
generative model for this context um and
i noticed you were you're citing the
work of um
manchester united uh you know and that
was i think he's really great
insight many years ago interesting from
economics he was working with economists
uh
at that time so so uh i think that's
very very important as well it's all
about estimating uncertainty
yeah thanks a lot um
i mean as you can see there is uh well
obviously we come from this this side of
uh
woolpert and you you can you can see all
that
all
that literature behind our work and uh
but yeah we're getting there and um
that's that's uh
that that's where we are going that's
what we're intending and you'll see some
some work that we're going to come out
uh very soon
that tries to to bring deeper this this
this um
to make more useful uh making better use
of this of this um
monitoring and the other thing i was
telling you i was thinking is something
you mentioned is this waiting of the
attenuation and and
that's always been in our in our mind
again because of uh why can you tickle
yourself and all these famous famous
works um
we have lots of doubts we have uh lots
of discussion with with with people
about this attenuation and and the
precision waiting and that's what we are
now trying to to implement
uh
again using self-organized maps but uh
yeah we we we try to get results quite
soon
and thanks a lot
yeah just just to say
i think that's really important because
as soon as you can get dynamic
dynamic
attenuation or gating
um in play very much in the spirit of
what was implicit in um
matt's um sort of homeostatic
architecture you can talk i think
genuinely you can talk about your your
robots attending to this or ignoring
that in the right kind of way and you're
starting i think to get quite close to
now
sentience because you've got attention
in the mix
you've got some a kind of metacognition
in your self-organizing maps which i
think license is something which is much
much closer now to sort of a sentient
intelligence
as opposed to just a reflexive kind of
control
yeah that that's that's that's the idea
let's let's hope for the best
so
a few
points and then adam or jacob or anyone
um active inference is inference about
action
and it also uses action as one of the
ways to reduce uncertainty and so it's a
very tantalizing parallel with quantum
active inference as being about quantum
systems
and potentially using quantum
in some way to run these models
another point was in the recent folk
psychology paper with with ryan smith at
all
there was a distinction of how
increasingly cognitive and symbolic
functions were being played by decision
making active inference in the discrete
setting while more motor behaviors could
be played out by motor active inference
in the continuous time setting
and through this conversation i'm seeing
how
whether that is explicit or implicit
that decision ai
to motor ai
handoff
is mediated by a symbolic layer
either implicitly through the code
construction
or potentially even explicitly with the
kinds of approaches that we're exploring
and then one last area of some parallels
that i'll
like to hear from adam or anyone else
self-organizing maps brought up by bruno
have a lot of similarities with some of
the graph operations
that tim ferbell and ozankittal and
adam's work was describing and then the
harmonic modes
that adam has described in work as well
reminded me of the ultra stability that
matt brown described in some of these
more classical models of like
synergetics and multi-scale harmonic
and so
adam or anyone else would be happy to
hear any of those thoughts
um okay just uh quickly to to answer
adam um
i don't know exactly
how
i mean what do you mean with
oh by the way they can't see my question
on the audience maybe we should read ah
sorry uh adam is asking to what extent
can self-organizing maps be used as
model of experience dependent plasticity
as implementing a kind of implicit
neural architecture search i mean i
don't know exactly what you mean with
neural architecture search but um
um there is this this um
literature on
growing self-organizing maps so like the
usual uh
original architecture is is fixed
but there is there is some
implementations where you actually can
add notes
and and they become more more well they
have more plasticity and there is also
the
the ones that don't stop learning so
it's it's continuously moving so that
helps you to not have a fixed structure
and a fixed mapping of the sensory input
but it's it just moves as there is new
data coming new input
coming in
so that's that's two dynamical sounds
and growing sums i think if if you are
interested in that
okay extremely uh
i guess the the intuition or question
was that
um it's like you know i'm sure there are
plenty of inductive biases that we
come equipped with to
help us converge on efficient regimes of
inference and learning
but i'm also wondering the extent to
which
um i don't want to go too far with this
kind of analogy but something kind of
like a field programmable gatorade but
like
um
that self-organizing map like dynamics
could allow for
um
the creation of different regimes of
active inference like like to what
extent
as you're like let's say um building up
a hierarchy
um
at different levels of it based on where
you are in this overall hierarchy or
hierarchy you might take on um very
different computational properties
um via experience kind of plasticity so
it's like
you you learn the inductive biases you
need as go um
but
to come back around with self-organizing
maps um
the locality and the the um
the topography of them
one thing i'm really curious about is
the extent which they could actually be
used for um modeling like um
enter rhino and hippocampal
representations to what degree the
different operations that are
um used for constructing these maps
would also
converge with them the kinds of
structural inference and structure
learning that have been
described for the hippocampal system so
um
i don't know the answers to that but it
seems like a potentially fruitful
intersection that daniel suggested
so yeah definitely yeah i mean
i think in principle they they are
inspired from the
hippocampal
activity you know the the maps
and
yeah there's lots of proposals out there
of different ways of moving them but uh
yeah i think
they they would be very useful for what
you want
so
that's why i'm talking about that like a
general
question for me that i'm i'm i've been
wondering about
is
so i guess i'm suggesting that like
you're getting these um represent these
um
representations structure
representations potentially being
um afforded by these uh place fields of
the chemical system
um but
one thing i'm wondering is so and that
these would provide like equilibrium
points like carl often we'll talk about
the importance of structuring action and
perception
um by these discrete acts that seem to
be unfolding at roughly theta
frequencies and this seems to be like
the time scale of coherent action
selection for an organism of about our
size that can do about the things we can
do with a brain about this big all kind
of brought in the same temporal register
um but
and so this idea that like we might be
stepping along these representations in
some ways like moving from like between
these bump attractors
um
as somehow structuring cognition by some
sort of representation
and i'm excited by that but i still
don't have like a sense like uh for how
far you go with that or ought to go like
for instance so let's say we're talking
about something like uh um
uh this is actually something uh uh
carlos that
scolded me about in the past which is
like before you like uh think of the
architectural principle think of the
inactive uh
situatedness of the system and so
something like i wonder is like so you
know i'm focusing like maybe you're
getting this sort of inductive bias of
like the hippocampus rhino system says
high level controller
but to what extent
are we implicitly doing
things like symbolic reasoning but via
like modes of enactment like to what
degree like could you do something like
like let's say we're kind of like
purling causation and you want to do
something like a do operator you could
have some sort of like graph some sort
of like flow of inference like um
maybe even like within like the like
chain bump attractors like the
hippocampal system and uh
actually another thing that carl
actually brought up recently was um bump
attractors and the colliculus so maybe
even like in terms like patterns of like
ocular motor motion is potentially like
providing like another means of
accessing such representations and being
governed by them uh
but
to to what extent it is um
is it too neurocentric is it actually
like being realized more implicitly by
the overall contextualized functioning
and like
it's you know having
open questions for me so
sure to carl and then jakub or anyone
else who wants to
talk to me
can i tell adam off again or not
i don't think he needs turning off um
yeah it's interesting isn't it um i
wonder whether that is the um the
interface that daniel was referring to
um how do you get from a necessary
continuous um
bayesian filter coupling with the world
i mean even with um carla and andy you
know these things are moving continuous
states better so at some point even if
it's actually um
physicalized you know there is a
continuous uh generative model or um
self-organization in play
and i'm reading um adam's question as
you know is this too neurocentric to to
worry about bump attractors and the role
of lateral inhibition for example in
carving up receptive fields that could
be actually written down as just sort of
basically a quantized representation you
know for example um
receptive fields in v5 or motion
sensitive areas can either be expressed
as a sort of continuous
preference for motion as a continuous uh
you know function of
visual velocity
or you can say no this population is
just encoding the probability that this
particular edge is moving at eight
degrees per second
um
so you know
if
if adam you were asking you know um
are we being too neurocentric in over
interpreting the neuronal dynamics that
just basically do the carving up into a
series of
either tilings and receptive fields or
place fields or in
the context of some stable fixed points
you know sort of um
thinking about
histoclinic channels as you know one way
of articulating a discrete set of
ordinarily organized uh fixed points
that have you know that's the way that
we should understand it i i don't know
but i think you know it could certainly
if you can read them in both ways
i think that then gives you license if
you want to simulate and reproduce and
silicone these kinds of computations it
certainly allows you to replace
heteroclinic channels um heterogeneous
cycles uh bump attractors receptive
fields of this kind with a discrete
representation
and you know
to me
practically that would be an important
and important way to proceed that's
simply because that minimizes the
complexity of the genetic model and it
minimizes the complexity you maximize
the uh the model evidence um so you know
i don't know whether being neurocentric
is um
as a good thing or a bad thing it you
know interesting just think about so
what is what what is a self-organizing
map um so when i was at school it was
just basically um
a uh
a couple map lattice with with lateral
inhibition to to um to do this sort of
uh carving up and segregate those
various populations um or localities
from other localities so if that's the
case again you've got this notion of
natural inhibition when i take all light
dynamics what is that well is that a
statement of this exclusion principle
and i mean beyond simply your
the the sort of exclusion principles i
can't be in one place at any one time
but the fundamental exclusion that you
get when dealing with discrete state
spaces you know i've got to be in this
state and i'm not in any other state
and that means that being in this state
means i have to inhibit being in any
other state
just to get a sum to one constraint so
just by going um if you like discrete
you're naturally inducing
by physical architecture that requires
the kind of lateral inhibition that is
one of the defining features of a
self-organizing map so that might be a
virtue uh or you know
of of being a bit neurocentric in the
sense of you know
understanding evolution as working its
way to a coarse brain minimally complex
discretized symbolic representation of
the world and we just now read receptive
fields in a slightly
oh we over interpret them they're just
you know basically
encodings i the world is likely to be in
this state from my point of view
can i just make one final point um
which kept on recurring to me that there
were people chasing you on this i'm
thinking about bruno and self-organizing
maps and adam in the uh and actually
matt as well with his um
i think there's a slow realization
that these kinds of architectures are
the way to go
that's coming out of machine learning
when people are getting bored with that
propagation so they're now all turning
to local energy
based rules and they now realize that
they get much better performance from a
deep neural network
if they just use a local energy based
rule and what would that look like it
would look exactly like the
self-organizer
self-organizing maps all three of you
been talking about it's just me my note
trying to predict everybody else around
me um uh you know
and doing so by minimizing my local
variation free energy or minimizing the
prediction errors uh you know
mathematically
those being equivalent
you know the twist here is that the
you know this can be applied to
effectively uh you know overly
expressive amorphous a completely
connected neural network and it will
still work with the right kind of
pruning you will start to get to the
sort of nice hierarchical structures
that bruno was showing uh or the you
know with the right kind of temporal
scheduling you'll get to the nice that
you're the nice uh tolmaneken bound
machines but at the end of the day these
are just um they're just sort of deep
networks or even deep that is networks
with a local um a local energy and those
things i've now noticed certainly in the
university of oxford are now called
predictive coding
so there's no necessary no prediction
there's no there's no prediction in the
temporal sense that adam was trying to
emphasize
or in the sense of a kalman filter it's
just that they rely upon the local
computation of prediction errors to
generate the local energy function
so i see you know the people the
reactionaries in deep learning you know
the young turks who want to do it better
they've all now identified predictive
coding as the rhetoric
in order to say this is how it's done
and it's just a statement of or your you
don't need to do um i think bruno had a
nice phrase do you or perhaps it was
perhaps it was um france fossil diffuse
your learning everywhere through back
propagation you if it's working properly
you should just be able to do it locally
with your own little
node
vertex of your som or gm in a
in an in your fonts
if i could uh build on that and then
anyone else who'd like to add
a challenge that exists and it's
recognized in robotics and many of the
presentations brought up was how to move
from continuous and high dimensional
data like a high resolution video camera
or multi-sensor integration
in the world
eventually
towards
logical and conditional contextual
action
and so when we see the neural network
representations we kind of see sometimes
zooming in and zooming out and different
ways that people are training those
models including limitations and those
models training like the back
propagation that carl just mentioned as
well as that stephen grossberg has gone
into
and so
trying to contextualize that issue in
light of what we're discussing about
discrete time and about symbolic logic
it seems that
through the partially observable
framework not even saying the partially
observable markovian framework but here
including holographic principle and so
on
there's a way to move from a continuous
statistical distribution and make a map
to a discrete statistical distribution
like the a matrix in the pomdps that we
use can have a continuous variable and
then map that onto a discrete
statistical distribution
and then
i wondered if there's something like a
logical a
another tale of two densities a tale of
two different cities or a third city and
so this matrix
recognizes logic
from discrete
distributions that's the recognition
density and then the generative density
is the emission of logics that are
compatible with discrete distributions
because
with the recognition direction
recognizing conditional logics and
searching over relatively small sets of
possible conditional logics from
discrete distributions is possible like
a verb is never used two verbs in a row
are not used or something like that
from a discrete distribution logic can
be extracted or recognized
and then
if there's a discrete distribution or
more
logics can be sampled and that speaks to
that inductive bias
where you want the inductive bias
to have
limited false positives and false
negatives with respect to the empirical
world like you wouldn't want to waste
time
spitting out logics that cannot be
however that might not be lethal but it
certainly wastes a lot of time and then
conversely what could be lethal would be
to have an inductive bias that fails to
recognize empirical aspects of the world
and so that is like an expectation
maximization
but transposing not between a continuous
and a discrete statistical space but
rather between a statistical and a
logical space
so jacob or oh yes
or bruno anyone who would like to add to
that please
no jaekov
you haven't said much please
but yeah i can say something afterwards
um yeah i just had some
general uh questions that are kind of
related to
um
daniel's remark on the move between the
purely continuous and statistical
representation of the generative models
into the discrete and
since this week i've been reading the
paper on
from chris fields and carl um and others
on the fep and
neuromorphic development i'm wondering
whether
the question of structure learning
can be
solved by
some fundamental computations that are
available at the very
low um
low dimensional level of just quantum
quantum systems where
given
given the right
environment that system would naturally
evolve into some kind of
discrete morphology that it didn't start
with kind of similar to like the
primordial soup then evolving into
discrete uh or
more discrete life forms
and whether
and whether that
might impose the
the nes the necessary um
structural learning principles where
or
[Music]
um
message passing where each le
each new layer that
evolves
in the hierarchy is receiving
observations from the other ones
given by
the new markov blanket that's
drawn around it
um
but then in terms of actual
implementation i uh
i'm wondering whether that requires
quantum computers or whether that can be
done with some kind of different
architecture that is able of this uh
automatic um
uh evolution in its morphology
also
bruno and then anyone else you'd like to
add
um yeah very i mean very nice your your
[Music]
your question and then um just kind of
to round up what what you were all
concerned about um we were just thinking
and remembering this this and going back
to sums
and there is this uh proposal some songs
but i don't remember the authors now but
it's this other type of architecture
that takes into consideration
the the learning progress so previous
activations and and some sort of history
of the winning previous winning uh notes
and so on
um
that might be
the next step so that you can actually
monitor what's happening over time and
if you have one of these that it's
coding for error then that would include
the the monitoring of of the prediction
error
yeah and and it would kind of close this
gap between continuous and discrete
representations because then you could
you could have it all over time
so i like if you one of them i can send
you some some literature on that that
thank you bruno
one point on the morphological
computational angle uh jacob and then
again anyone can raise their hand
i thought about
a bunch of tree
seeds
we're back in frequentism again so
everyone can take a breath but you know
there's a hundred seeds that are planted
and depending on the priors
inherited from evolution
and the updates which are happening from
the generative process from the niche
there's gonna be like a distribution
of that tree through time
so like a palm tree is gonna have a very
like narrow
cone
some sort of distributional cone across
those hundred that are sampling from it
and then another
a shrub might have like a different um
shape
then you brought up how potentially
quantum or discrete like
morphological decisions
could realize
that continuous
probability
distribution at the population or even
like the multiple worlds level
and there's something there also with
the local computation of large models
that carl mentioned that it's like
something happens
where there is not even just a symbolic
or a discrete decision that's made
there's an embedded decision that's
being made that now is part of the
history and so the branching pattern of
any given
palm tree is going to be unique or any
given
shrub
yet they also may
fill out at the population level
a distribution set
that has these aspects that can be
modeled as like a gaussian blur over
tree morphologies yet of course no one
is saying that the tree is a blur
and so there's so many interesting
contrasts with like the realized
trajectory of the lego robot
and that's the n equals one
the population of trajectories the
imagined set of trajectories
so having a unified ontology
to be able to talk
and have formal
concise connections
amongst these different kinds of
remembered now casted
anticipated or imagined futures
helps find
the patterns across systems
that like adam said are essentially the
basis of sense making and insight
i gotta ramble
um
so
i guess in terms of this like um
motion from a continuous to a discrete
regime
or even like um
drawing analogies from like a quantum to
like a more classical
regime
there's a in general like i've been kind
of like with respect to computational
models of consciousness wondering um
how
um a seemingly classical world of
experience can emerge from a problem
like why are things so precise
and or um
carl's written some really uh
interesting papers with andy clark on
this
um on the bayesian blur problem and one
of the suggestions was that like
um
the discretization for the sake
of action
like in order to act you have to act in
a particular way and it's like just the
requirements
of doing a particular thing at a
particular time induces this
and so one of the things um and so this
is
i don't think it's come uh
competing but in some ways competes for
like a suggestion i had all those things
compatible because like i was wondering
whether basically like um
something about the the time scales in
which you could get like these
um
coherent eigen modes or like the
population activity could achieve these
like attracting states
would create like the time skills of the
formation of these large-scale
attractors could create like an in and
out
of like who gets to inform or not and
this could help to like sharpen things
up
and and like creating these population
level attractors but there's another way
of describing it in terms of like what
lets you act
um so
in terms of like
uh
like these different
it's one more comment along those lines
is um
i think it's interesting that like so um
i've talked to some rodent researchers
and
you
when you remove the hippocampus you'll
still actually get
um
like roughly theta stale
theta scale
um
like
large mesoscale
organization of brain dynamics for the
rest of
the rodents nervous system
so it seems like there's almost a um
it might be and i don't know if you see
it's like degenerate but it's like
natural selection
like any mode any any way it could
catalyze things to help with the
coordination to help with
the alignment the spatial temporal
alignment of um
that allow that collab for different
forms of synchronization
um
was utilized so like there's like you
could get for instance a good amount of
discretization just from like
potentially just from like learning and
interacting with the world that requires
you to do this just physically to
interface with it you get some of it
from like the overall um
connectomic properties just like that's
the times like um
that's what's required for the the you
know the overall brain to form
attractors that they'll form at a
certain time scale and different nervous
systems of different size and complexity
with different bottle like information
bottlenecks might tend to form these
attracting states roughly
on that same scale and maybe things are
tuned for that or maybe they get tuned
by experience either as an innate
inductive bias or as a
empirical uh meta prior learning or
learned
you'd also get it with things like the
local logic of like um how you
transition between these different
equilibrium points for like highly
central structures
and so um something is very unclear to
me is like the extent i imagine the
answer is like all of you above
in like most combinations but it's like
to what degree
um
[Music]
were these um inductive biases are they
taking the form of evolutionary priors
and to what degree are they
developmental priors this is still very
unclear to me um but one thing that um
and there seems to be a tension in uh
machine learning in terms of these like
you want these rich inductive priors to
do efficient inference and learning
because otherwise it's hopeless but you
pay a price in terms of generalization
sometimes
and so i have no idea how nature
balances
to what extent in what cases um all
right i have some idea but not nearly
enough to feel comfortable
so anyways that's my ramble
i think we can actually hinge on this
and bring it to an area that some of the
registrants
brought up and also something probably
many of us have been thinking about
which is multi-agent modeling
and i wanted to connect that to what
adam was just saying um
about
what is granted
via embeddedness
what arises or becomes more possible
simply as a function of realized
corporal embodiment as opposed to
in silico simulation
and in our multi-agent discussions
we've been differentiating spatial
multi-agent scenarios
from
essentially non-spatial like digital or
cognitive so in the spatial multi-agent
case
the real world the niche the generative
process does the work of inducing or
preventing collisions like it just
cannot be the case that two entities are
in the same location
whereas in the cognitive case whether
it's bird song or a negotiation or
verbal communication or visiting
websites we can both be at the same
website and so then there's sort of a
mass parallel stigma g occurring or a
mass parallel real-time architecture
where there is some kind of coordination
but the coordination isn't exclusionary
again because two entities could their
thought trains could essentially cross
in and out and those trains are like
ghost trains that don't exclude each
other whereas that couldn't happen in
the real world
so
i wanted to ask anyone who had thoughts
how does multi-agent modeling come into
play for robotics
what current issues are facing
multi-agent robotics
and how can what we're discussing here
with active inference play a role
specifically in understanding complex
multi-agent scenarios
i i have a question in that regard uh
for matt
matt your solution has been applied to a
single agent
uh do you see the
possibility of a homeostat that is
composed of multiple agents
that will direct their collaboration
towards achieving
a common goal does it scale to
multi-agent
situations
thanks i hope matt can provide a thought
as is
working carl and then anyone else
where is matt
listening
oh is he can he speak
only at a future point in an expected
trajectory i will answer for him then i
would imagine uh what he would say is if
you just take the the generalized
synchrony uh perspective on with the
emerging properties of a homeostat
coupled to its environment and you
couple two homeostats together they will
find a mutual homeostasis that just will
be a joint synchronization manifold so
what you'd expect to see is a coming
together exactly um um in the spirit of
uh dynamical generalized synchronization
and so
there will be as i think daniel
mentioned earlier on though
the homeostats will be singing from the
same hymn sheet under the constraints of
what they can communicate
um so um so
from i think from matt's point of view
he's more interested though in
establishing a generalized synchrony
between a a use case an industrial use
case
and his homeostat as opposed to just
letting two homeostats you know shape
and design their own little economy
indulgence sort of cultural niche
construction while i'm talking though
that it was a nice uh
something very interesting about
daniel's question in relation to to your
work um
i i sort of overheard the little robots
telling each other what they were
thinking um and i thought that was
really important um
and simply because um
you know speaking to this general
question about you know what does active
inference or what
[Music]
what are the special considerations that
you might want to bring to the table
when thinking about a multi-agent um
setting i think
there are two ways we could talk about
ages about this first of all it's having
the law of requisite variety across
agents and then the story would unfold
in terms of natural selections bayesian
model selection and that would i think
answering large parts of adam's
questions about where the inductive
biases come from if you cast that the
biases as selection biases we're just
talking about basic model selection
selection amongst what the requisite
varieties afforded by ashby's law uh but
to make that bayesian model selection
work you have to have natural selection
um so you know there's a great story
about the importance of um multiple
agents
um from that point of view from the
point of view of structure learning
for free as an emergent property of
of natural basic model selection or
natural structural learning
but the other the other thing is um
just from the point of view of active
inference if you've got multiple agents
um what's to stop you thinking about
these multiple agents as one big agent
where you've cut some message passing
between them um and like one big agent
with lots and lots of eyes and sensors
and the like
so i'm asking now when i looked at carla
and andy
what's to stop me thinking about carla
and andy as one agent
that has a really um flexible and
deployable set of sensors so they've got
eyes that can point in different
directions so if we translate this into
sort of um
uh you know controlling drones for
example and we have a swarm of drones we
can think about that as one agent one
robot with lots of deployable eyes which
gives you you know
an enormous flexibility um over uh
you know and possibly complexity of the
way that we control our two eyes which
are both in front of our heads
um so how would you then write down a
concerted model for a swarm of eyes
where there's one cpu there's one um
there's one sort of uh
the lego brick
controlling all the the drones uh where
you just write a generative model with
multiple sensory modalities where you
needed to deploy action in the right
kind of way to get the right epistemic
foraging or whatever um
but that would entail now um message
passing belief updating um lateral
interactions and an some
between the brains of agents
so say oh you can't do that you've
actually got to have physically
separable robots to have a multi truly
multi-agent set up
so how can you now
work around the fact you you don't have
direct message passing and belief
updating between the two the brains the
the brain the separated brains when you
just have communication so provided you
broadcast what you believe
and provided those beliefs are
perspective
independent so they're conserved
from you know so that they you know what
i say in terms of my frame of reference
um is meaningful from your point of
frame of reference which incidentally
for daniel and uh jacob
becomes relevant from point of quantum
frames of reference here but if we can
assume we're all got the same we've all
got an
alice-centric frame of reference then
all of it is required to put together
the
the many brains into one brain um is to
have beliefs broadcast
just those beliefs that that will that
will um that are conserved or shared in
the uh the ensembles generative model so
you know i don't know
where your was carla able to hear
andy and vice versa
so when did did they actually share a
narrative in a belief updating
no they did not they they uh the the
the speaking was uh the talking was
mostly for my benefit so i could see
what was going in their mind at the time
so when when uh uh carl was saying oh
andy is freaking out i knew that the
journal of model had identified the
behavior and and and
inferred
the mindset of the other robot
but i i am uh playing with the idea that
they can communicate um
by just distributed message
passing from one robot to the other and
what they would communicate
is is uh
essentially
if
i would consider one agent as as a
source of sensation
for another agent and and in the same
way that internally journal models uh
the beliefs of a general model becomes a
sensation
of of another higher level genetic model
that could scale across multiple agents
and and that would happen by
communicating
these
predictions across agents in this
prediction errors across agent as they
propagate between general evolves within
a single agent and just scale the
architecture so instead of having a
society of mind within an agent which
would also have a society of minds
across agent in the same mechanisms
would be at play but you're absolutely
right we need to have this communication
but it would be the same kind of
communication
within
uh across society of minds as they would
be within society of mind i'm hoping
that they would be self-similar
and the same architecture would apply at
any scale
which actually speaks to jacob's
question uh about your mark off blankets
and mark off blankets and sort of you
know that sparse do you get from from
that scale-free
separation and you know refined
minimally complex message passing i
think there's something quite
fundamental there about you know the
nature of communities and the
the scale of the world in which we live
and all the organs that comprise me
living in that world that that scale
free aspect that is defined by the
sparsity and the absence of coupling and
and getting the messages that are
communicated right i i think something
quite fundamental about that
i got a question adam please
um
so for the internal
uh
organism internal case i'm wondering so
to what degree do you get um common
agency for
um societies of minds due to common
embodiment but when we're going for a
kind of
common
uh or joint agency
and
maybe even different forms of joint
identification or de-individuation
um
or re-individuation of individuals into
a collective
um to what degree do we need something
like um
as constraining as a joint embodiment
like for instance like i'm thinking of
like um
uh soldiers marking and like marching in
step or like the ways in which like we
kind of like seem to like potentially
even like expand and hack our body maps
by like sharing like
different synchronous modes you know
that literature is somewhat contested um
i like the literature but um the
but to what degree is it
you don't need to have that kind of
synchrony though it's just like a strong
enough shared task
is enough to like
um
radically make someone uh
make the central thing their role of
where they're singing in the hem sheet
that becomes the primary attractor
governing them and you don't need to
like um
necessarily have this this kind of
physicality
i don't know if that makes sense but
like i'm think of the different means in
which you yes do you need something like
synchronous in time or is it just a very
strong
pressure selective pressure for
coordination to establish a
synchronization manifold
to create to pull off the
re-individuation
oh it's a great question adam so thank
you
i also
think this ties to again js framing of
society of mind and then we can contrast
that with a society of bodies so the
society of mind
is that virtualized case
whether it's the counterfactual
virtualizations that cognitive entities
can be modeled as doing or whether it
might even be a society of minds in a
digital setting
and then there's the societies of bodies
which maps earlier to our multi-agent
discussion on like a physical crowd so
like what are the similarities and
differences with the digital swarm and a
physical one
it comes down a lot to their ability to
collide and again the digital swarm can
weave in and out because they can
coexist in the same location in a
semantic space in that generalized
foraging way whereas the embodied swarm
is going to have collision
prevention
by virtue of the physicality
and i think by using active inference to
study these systems and integrate them
we do approach exactly what you brought
up adam which is like
almost
what do we
get
through shared tasks
as opposed to what do we get from a
common task something that we merely
have in common
versus something that we're actively
coordinating on together
and potentially even coordinating
together in the same exact space or on
the same instance of which provides the
most constraints like if people are
rowing the same boat versus rowing
parallel boats versus on different lakes
so as we sort of
separate spatially
and especially virtualize there becomes
more and more possibilities
um and this for those who are coming for
perhaps from a robotics angle
and wanting to understand what active
inference brings to the picture here
hopefully we've
pointed a few things like the scale-free
or scale-friendly nature
of models to be composed based upon
their sparsity and defined interfaces
and also the multi-modal aspect for
example carl asked jf if the audio could
be heard
rather than only emitted
and that's not going to require some
bolted on communication module
it is going to be able in the symbolic
or in the numerical case
to be mapped onto an architecture that
also
bruno showed these architectures that
can do
sensor integration
as a function of the interface
definitions locally
rather than potentially have ad hoc
structural design decisions
that could result in a lot of research
and engineering debt
so happy to hear any
thoughts on that
um
yes god
yeah i mean
yeah you're right and
um no i just wanted to add that we are
working on
on that community well
first
um
i come from from the very i don't know
like a very
now you could call it old-fashioned
school where we were
we
as you can see in our implementations
they are
kind of very low level what we could say
low level and and coming from the
sensory
interaction with the world and
that that is maybe why we are not or we
haven't been so far very concerned with
very high level representations known so
we are just dealing with very basic
interaction with the world
and at the same time
it's it's my belief i mean it's very
interesting this interaction between
agents and so on but i think or we
i've always thought that first we need
an agent that that knows itself in the
world
and and has an uh its own model so like
a first frontier or a first blanket uh
as you like to call them
um
and only then
can
start to understand other agents and to
to interact with other agents
um
yeah so
that that was what i wanted to tell you
know thyself
carl
there is an argument from um
developmental neural robotics that
to have a true sense of self you you've
got to have a true sense of other and
you can only ever have a true sense of
other if there's something else out
there that's physically very much like
you so just i'm speaking now to adam's
uh point does it have to be uh or
perhaps daniel's question you know the
the
the shared body as opposed to the shared
the shared narrative you there
there is an argument uh i'm not
making the argument i'm just saying that
there could be an argument
that in order to disambiguate the causes
of some sensory consequences of an
action
from
where the action could be made by you or
an identical robot or me or mum
or me or my brother
that is the only case in which you are
now going to be a need to
contextualize
and assign and attribute the agency of
this outcome to what to self versus
other in a world in which i was the only
object or phenotype like me i would need
a sense of self and i wouldn't need a
sense of other it's just when you have
multiple agents that are quite similar
and confusable
um then you actually need a sense of
self to make sure it's not it's you and
not me um which of course you know
speaks to not only theory of mind but
you know the essence of communication as
well so i'm just making that point that
you know um
they're putting two robots together
maybe as you point out once you've
sorted out a robot just learning how to
move um then
learning that
the consequences of it moving
could actually be reproduced by somebody
else and then it might develop a sense
of selfhood a minimal sense of selfhood
and then i think you're in the game of
true theory of mind that's uh
yeah it's a very interesting area with
thinking through other minds as have
been brought up in some of the
presentations and then society of mind
it is that
nesting of blankets of different kinds
of generative models but again using the
same statistical or formal machinery
just like we could have a nested
multi-level regression model where one
model was in kilometers and then there
was another model that was in degrees
for temperature
[Music]
and also the question about swarms and
collectives and groups
comes up in biology all the time
with different ways that people delimit
or qualify individuality
ranging from the evolutionary unit of
replication the kantian concept of an
organism as the unit that is
teleologically closed the physiological
individuality which might even include
cases like symbioses the information
theory of individuality and different
ways that
uh
we can look at information processing
and transfer in terms of what
individuals are
and uh
it's so fascinating how that comes into
play with robotics
where when we think about the
robots that will be interacting with us
as a slightly different set than the
ones that might be working
underwater on a pipeline
there like like matt showed they might
be able to interact with a relatively
simple generative process that doesn't
exhibit mind-like qualities
it's interacting with a mere active
inference entity but when on the other
side of the blanket there's another
adaptive active inference entity
and especially when it's us
then there's a space of
norms
and also laws
which are like that pseudo code
execution order
for thinking through other minds in a
way
how will robots navigate a space
and how will they be able to make
abduction
occur in a real-time way both in the
generation of novel hypotheses with
inductive bias
followed by the selection
of
trajectories of action
again taking into account
formal codified law
as well as the kind of state of
exception even or understanding when
preferences allow for something to be so
strongly desired
that
how and when
it's uh
pursued
might not be how you pursue it in a
different time so there's just a lot of
cool threats yes adam and anyone else
um this is reminding me also from the uh
first session
uh uh there was mention of value
alignment
and like this seems to be like a a
multi-scale problem in terms of like it
will show up just as much of like the
robot not stepping on your toes or you
know crushing your foot
to like um as it expands you know does
it uh is it is it optimizing in the
direction are its tensors going the
direction that you want your tensors to
go of
shaping
um and
it seems like of the proposals sometimes
there's um
how did i say this like
uh
begged questions that active inference
may be answers so it's sort of like
let's say you have a framework like
cooperative inverse reinforcement
learning and so there's some sort of
like you know so it's like you are
trying to like
roughly like optimize for the utility
function of the other agent so how do
you get this kind of like shared utility
but in like these like active inference
models where like you're bootstrapping
minds um
like intersubjectively you have like
regimes of joint attention and thinking
through other minds or i mean some of
this work with them uh
i'm doing with anna uh chinitsa it's
like she emphasizes how like we start
out like
actually physically inside of another
organism completely dependent like
homeostatically and so like you're
you're automatically sort of um
grandmothering in
this joint intention right from the
get-go
and
the seeds of um you know organization
and individuation are already like you
know scaffolded in that way just by the
um just by by the niche
contextualization where you are
co-constructing each other as your
mutual and you and me are
inter-subjective like mutual niche
construction
so it seems like um with respect to the
um i don't know at what point these
problems in terms of like deploying
robots when they first enter because you
know it's it's all you know always
highfalutin as like intelligence
explosions really like a recursively
amplifying system stay aligned with you
but just like
in the world
you know how can i make sure the robot
like
doesn't crush my foot like i don't
anyway so um
the ways in which um co-valuing and um
the the robot identifying itself as an
individual relative to other individuals
plays into it
it seems like active inference has like
a very rich way of handling and modeling
a lot of these different um uh
proposals and processes but um something
i wonder like from to ask like actual
roboticists like how near-term is it
like a live problem of getting like
what forms of social modeling for robots
like and what forms of like a sense of
self modeling for the robot like
how much do we need at what stage for
what levels of deployment in the world
with what degrees of robustness
simple question
great question
and maybe just uh to double on what
active inference does to potentially
frame that junction since
in this round table we won't address but
this is
the stuff and substance of applied
active inference symposia for many years
to come
in an economic framework
a reward absolutist framework
which is kind of a full stack ranging
from the ways that models are trained
based upon pragmatic value and reward
all the way up through a world that
values economic returns
the question becomes in human robot
alignment or in multi-agent alignment
more generally the question becomes how
are we creating
and then allocating epistemic i'm sorry
how are we creating and then allocating
pragmatic value and epistem can be
valued to the extent that through time
it provides pragmatic value for example
one person doing a little bit more of a
research angle and one doing more of an
application and profit side of the
business
and when we shift
to a uncertainty imperative
for a sustainable or even optimistic
world model
then we can achieve pragmatic value
as a consequence of a process theory
that highlights reduction of uncertainty
and then the question moves from
creating and allocating value
to
how can this ecosystem of diverse
entities
find a general synchrony and communicate
and
be how they are
in a way that will be
reducing the expected free energy of the
ensemble
which is not the question that was even
approached by the
create value allocate value framing
that has come up in ai and continues to
occur to this day
what if the image creators what if they
end up reducing our food allocation so
they can have more they take the
intellectual property instead of
providing it to humans
that might be framed slightly
differently in an uncertainty reduction
framework plus
optimism
rather than in a reward maximization
which somewhat enforces a atomism and
even a pessimism
that was an excellent point yeah
yeah
there are so many ways you can tackle
that and i'm still puzzling over adam's
charge how do you stop robots standing
on your foot
i was thinking how do you stop little
puppy dogs wing on the carpet um you
know i i think it's really going to
train them haven't you really i don't
think there's any magic answer
i think the answer is just what daniel
said you know uh things are designed and
um can presumably only exist under the
free energy principle
um if they um minimize their uncertainty
or expected surprise so that they make
everything as predictable as possible
which simply means that if i'm living in
a world full of dogs robots cats flies
and plants um then we're all trying to
make ourselves as predictable as
possible to each other
and that is the you know that's a sort
of folk psychological way of saying that
um
variation free energy is an extensive
quantity so if a set of um markov
blankets or phenotypes of varying forms
and structures
jointly
has its own markov blanket so it is an
ensemble or a group or a community or a
family um then it must put an upper
bound on its surprise and free energy
and because the free energy of each
constituent of that ensemble
is
summed to give the joint free energy
then it also
requires that each individual is trying
to minimize her surprise at the same
time it's all internally consistent and
quite you know to my mind unmagical um
if you just look at it in terms of
minimizing free energy or minimizing
optim surprise under optimism was
telling all that supported
thanks
you'd have to make your dog surprised
when he wheeze so you've got to find a
way of making the robot surprised when
it stands it stands on your on your
foot jf you have a
dog
right so how do you see similarities and
differences with these versions
of and also potentially even a family so
how do you see these different entities
being um
communicating and and behaving
appropriately or not and learning
well that's
having a dog it raises the question of
do i make myself understood
and that's a very that's a very
difficult question to answer when i say
no you're not allowed to eat from that
plate on the table
i think my dog understands i'm not
allowed to do this now
as soon as i walk out then permission is
granted
so i
you know it's it's difficult to
communication is very difficult across
across individuals especially across the
species
but i'd like to to just
just rant a little bit on something
which
came up which is uh the scale-free
nature of free energy principle the fact
that it can apply at a societal level
the same way that it applies like a
russian doll
to the cellular level
as a software developer
i see self-similarity
the recursion
fractal as as a as a beautiful thing and
i think at the
same way physicists have symmetries
as as a guide to what is
right because it's beautiful
i think we share
um self-similarity
as as a guide as what is beautiful and
possibly
true and i think self-similarity
is beautiful because it's it's it
it's
it's collapses the amount of information
that you need to generate something rich
um so that's why i think that having
a society of mind made up of actors and
having a society of minds
uh and having the same principles scale
up uh
feels very beautiful and
feels right
excellent
um yes just if we could go for any any
length of time a final set of thoughts
and reflections from each of you
quick interjection uh jf if you have
anything written on that or want to
write it there's an upcoming special
issue on symmetries that
i think it might fit with
would you like to
give any final reflections or anything
that you've heard
or felt updated by
any thoughts you have on
the state of the applied active
inference
in 2022 in robotics or where we're
heading now that this symposium is
behind us
i'll start with adam but then everyone
else can go
um
thank you daniel
well this simulated a lot of questions
and just seeing the range of work being
done was inspiring and um all i have to
say is i was grateful to be a part of
this
thank you for putting this together
thank you adam and
after the closing words i'll review
every presentation and list the
co-organizers as well so bruno and then
we'll continue on
yeah just just like adam said thanks a
lot for the invitation it was it was
very kind of you i think i want to thank
mark for insisting mark miller that was
insisting on us
to present with you here um it was it
was a very nice experience and
well we keep we we keep working we need
more hands
we have more ideas than hands but i
suppose that's everyone's problem no so
yeah thanks a lot
great
then there were three
[Music]
uh-huh
jf
yes well again thank you very much this
was extremely stimulating
every talk i came up i came out
listening to it with
this i want to introduce in my robots
some aspect of it uh and my mind is is
buzzing right now with with
possibilities and so thank you so much
for this opportunity
i guess uh
i can go next also
thanks a lot for uh
um being able to
join this this final round table and for
all of the
great presentations i'll definitely have
to
look over them
uh
probably a couple couple more times uh
to fully
uh understand all the
progress that um
has been has been made and specific
specifically on there's a lot of a lot
to consider on
the multi-agent uh modeling and
the ideas uh in this discussion that
uh
we were also talking about quite a lot
in the active block friends uh project
um
probably was left with uh
more more questions at the at the end of
it but that's also the exciting part of
it so
thanks a lot
and now it's my turn i cleverly leave
myself to last because everything that
needs to be said has already been said
so that just means
all i have to do is just to thank daniel
and his colleagues which he's going to
thank anyway but personally to daniel
thanks so much for all your energy not
just today but over the years it is
really great to see these people
and coys come together and sort of you
know generate ideas and questions which
is exactly what we need to do
thank you
thanks a lot carl and i think by one
personal reflection
it swooped in at the end when jf said
that at
from each of the presentations there was
like a module or an archetype or a
function that transposed and i think
that is proof of concept of working in a
shared ontology as well as in an
embodied
shared ontology which is to say like a
field in a community of practice
with different small world structures
and so on but when we have the ability
to transpose across systems and scales
then we can bring in
the modules and the pieces that people
are mentioning
and start to understand how those
functions can be composed and designed
and that's extremely exciting
everyone thanks for joining the round
table you can depart the zoom or i'm
just going to review the uh presenters
again and the co-organizers so thank you
for joining the round table you can
leave if you'd like
in the first session
there was
tim schneider with active inference for
robotic manipulation
tim verbellen
robots modeling the world from pixels
using deep active inference
ben white artificial empathy active
inference and collective intelligence
norse jeet learning agent preferences
and wen hua chen
dual control for exploitation and
exploration and its applications in
robotic autonomous search
then in the first round table it was
wenhua and i
talking about
dual control
the second session
began with bruno lara with prediction
error dynamics a proof of concept
implementation matt brown real-time
robotic control through embodied
homeostatic feedback
and atom saffron with generalized
simultaneous localization and mapping
g-slam as unification framework for
natural and artificial intelligences
towards reverse engineering the
hippocampal enterinal system and
principles of high-level cognition
and then jf cloud here
towards a symbolic implementation of
active inference for lego robots
we've just completed the second round
table with adam bruno jf carl jacob and
i
the organizers for the symposium were
mark miller
matt brown
blue knight
alex vyatkin
yvonne metelkin and myself
so
thanks again
till number three of applied active
inference hope to see everyone around
the institute
bye
you